<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Directions for love and marriage in two books / written originally by Franciscus Barbarus, a Venetian senator ; and now translated into English by a person of quality.</title>
            <title>De re uxoria. English. 1677</title>
            <author>Barbaro, Francesco, ca. 1398-1454.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30867</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B683A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40747</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18892134</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18892134</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108455</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30867)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108455)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1680:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Directions for love and marriage in two books / written originally by Franciscus Barbarus, a Venetian senator ; and now translated into English by a person of quality.</title>
                  <title>De re uxoria. English. 1677</title>
                  <author>Barbaro, Francesco, ca. 1398-1454.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 128 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Leigh ... and Tho. Burrell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with print show-through and slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Women --  History --  Renaissance, 1450-1600.</term>
               <term>Women --  Social conditions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:108455:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108455:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:108455:2"/> 
               <hi>LICENSED.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Novemh. 3. 1676.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Roger L'Eſtrange.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108455:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> DIRECTIONS FOR LOVE AND MARRIAGE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In two Books.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written Originally by <hi>Franciſcus Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barus</hi> a <hi>Venetian</hi> Senator.</p>
            <p>And now Tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by a Perſon of Quality.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Leigh</hi> at the <hi>Bell,</hi> and <hi>Tho. Burrell</hi> at the <hi>Golden-Ball,</hi> under St. <hi>Dunſtans Church,</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1677.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:108455:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:108455:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Reatiſes of this nature perhaps may not be very welcome to ſome who too much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining to the licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious humour of this depraved Age, decry Marriage as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint upon their Liberty. Their more refined wits ſcorning to tread one ſtep in the beaten paths of their wiſer Anceſtors, and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
<pb facs="tcp:108455:4"/> explode that which all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and all Ages, the wiſeſt Men, and even God himſelf hath allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as ſacred. Though I fear it will not pleaſe ſome, yet I hope it may not be unſeaſonable to prevent others, from adhering to ſee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions and impolitick an opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This Treatiſe was firſt writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in <hi>Italian,</hi> and ſo well liked of that it was tranſlated into <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> and printed in <hi>Holland,</hi> where it hath gained an Univerſal Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe. It is now at laſt tranſlated for the benefit of the Engliſh Reader, from the generality of whom it hopes for a favourable reception.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:108455:4"/>
            <head>The Table of the Chapters of the firſt Book. <hi>Concerning the Endowments of a Wife.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <label>CHAP. I.</label>
               <item>WHat Wedlock is, and what are its advantages.</item>
               <label>CHAP. II.</label>
               <item>With what qualifications and manners a Wife ſhould be choſen.</item>
               <label>CHAP. III.</label>
               <item>Concerning the Age of a Wife to be choſen.</item>
               <label>CHAP. IV.</label>
               <item>Concerning the Nobility of a Wife to be choſen.</item>
               <label>CHAP. V.</label>
               <item>Concerning the Beauty of a Wife to be choſen.</item>
               <label>CHAP. VI.</label>
               <item>Concerning the Riches of a Wife to be choſen.</item>
               <label>CHAP. VII.</label>
               <item>Concerning the importance of time and of other things to change our purpoſes.</item>
               <label>CHAP. VIII.</label>
               <item>Concerning Nuptial Solemnities.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:108455:5"/>
            <list>
               <head>The Table of the Chapters of the ſecond Book. <hi>Concerning the Duty of a Wife.</hi>
               </head>
               <label>CHAP. I.</label>
               <item>Concerning Gonjugal Love.</item>
               <label>CHAP. II.</label>
               <item>Concerning the moderation of a Wife.</item>
               <label>CHAP. III.</label>
               <item>Concerning the ſpeech and ſilence of Women.</item>
               <label>CHAP. IV.</label>
               <item>Concerning the Apparel and Attire of a Wife.</item>
               <label>CHAP. V.</label>
               <item>Concerning the Food of a Wife.</item>
               <label>CHAP. VI.</label>
               <item>Concerning the regulation of Congreſs.</item>
               <label>CHAP. VII.</label>
               <item>Concerning Domeſtick care.</item>
               <label>CHAP. VIII.</label>
               <item>Concerning the Education of Children.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:108455:5"/>
            <head>DIRECTIONS FOR <hi>Love and Marriage.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="book">
               <head>BOOK I.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. I. <hi>What Wedlock is, and what are its advantages.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall firſt treat of a few things before I begin to diſcourſe concerning the choice and duty of a Wife. Firſt I purpoſe to define in this place what Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock is, that (after the Example of Learned Perſons) it may in the beginning be underſtood what will be the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:108455:6"/> Subject of our future Diſcourſe. For ſo, the Sum of the Matter being known, we may more eaſily, and rightly judge of the reſt. Wedlock is therefore a perpetual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of Man and Wife, lawfully inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, for the propagating of Iſſue, or avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fornication; whereof there have been many and divers Opinions. It would be tedious to enquire and to argue which of theſe is the true; but the Opinion as well of the Eminent Pagans as of the Chriſtians, which by the conſent of almoſt all Men is accounted praiſe-worthy, ſeems better to me.</p>
                  <p>For the <hi>Romans</hi> (that the City might be repleniſhed with Legitimate Iſſue) enacted that thoſe who lived a ſingle Life until old Age, ſhould be obliged to pay Money (cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Mulcts) into the Treaſury; for they would follow Nature it ſelf, by which a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Congreſs for Procreation ſake is communicated to every kind of Animals, and which accounts her happineſs to conſiſt in thoſe which are Procreated. For the Senſe of Generation alſo is apparent in Beaſts: For truly (that I be not tedious in ſpeaking of other things) we all ſee a deſire in Birds of building their Neſts, in which is obſervable a certain Repreſentation
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:108455:6"/> of Wedlock to beget and nouriſh their like. By this means even as the Body is nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Meat, ſo the Offspring of Men and Beaſts is perpetuated.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lycurgus</hi> (by whoſe excellent Laws the Republick of the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> flouriſhed, but being neglected was overthrown) hath branded them with Ignominy, who continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Celibacy thirty ſeven years; and he prohibited them, who as yet had not attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Nuptial State to appear at the Wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-Schools, that they being inflamed with a deſire either of ſhunning Reproach, or by the nobleneſs of the Reward, the City might become greater and more glorious with Free-men. Wherefore a certain young Man, who for his honour ſake departed not from the Theatre, did very wittily apply this ſaying to <hi>Calicla</hi> the famous Emperour, who had no Children at <hi>Lacedaemon</hi> where was the honourable Harbour of his old Age, Neither have you O <hi>Calicla</hi> begotten me to depart.</p>
                  <p>It hath been experienced that by Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Marriages Children are more diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Birth to honeſty, more gravely edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, and become better Citizens, of whom the City conſiſting, will be more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to its Friends in Juſtice, more ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:108455:7"/> to its Enemies in Valour: For Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (that Miſtreſs) hath made it moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that thoſe who are unlawfully and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperately Begotten, for the moſt part are flagitious and diſhoneſt, and more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe to wickedneſs. The Luſtre of their paternal glory does not permit them who are Legitimately born to be obſcure, who are ſenſible that the Trophees of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents brings more Burden than Honour, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs their own Virtue correſpond to the Dignity and Amplitude of their Anceſtors. Neither truly are they ignorant, that expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and (as it were) the repetition of Hereditary Virtue turns the Eyes of all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves: So we may term thoſe, who are Born to Repute, The Walls of a City. When a certain Perſon complained <hi>(Ageſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> being preſent) that <hi>Lacedaemon</hi> wanted Walls, he ſaid, O ye Gods grant better things! Our City it ſelf is its own ſtrongeſt Wall. For indeed it is fit that we preſerve and defend our Country, Gods, Houſhold-Gods, Altars, Houſes, Parents, Wives and Children, not by Wood or Brick, but by Valour. What alſo is more pleaſant than to prevent a common want by dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick care? and to have a chaſte Woman, who may be a ſociable and friendly Wife
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108455:7"/> in proſperous and adverſe Affairs? To whom you may diſcloſe your moſt ſecret thoughts concerning her Affairs? To whom you may commit your little and mutual Children? In whoſe ſpeech and pleaſantneſs you may lay aſide all your cares and griefs? Whom you may ſo love, that you eſteem ſome part of your Life included in her wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare? <hi>Cato</hi> the Cenſor thought that there was ſo much Reſpect and Veneration due to this ſtate, that whoſoever ſhould offer vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to his Wife, he publickly affirmed, was equally to be proſecuted and deteſted with the violators of the Images of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſes; and it's related that he was wont to ſay, that he thought it more difficult to be a good Husband, than to be a good Senator. By this tye <hi>Caduſius</hi> reconciled the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious <hi>Carians</hi> amongſt themſelves; by this alliance <hi>Cyrus</hi> appeaſed the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> that were at enmity with their Borderers; and at <hi>Rome</hi> in the ſame day the <hi>Sabins</hi> were both Enemies and Citizens. This ſame thing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed the minds of <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Caeſar</hi> that were eſtranged. And what is more incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be ſpoken, <hi>Alexander</hi> by this affinity, (but not by that ſtately Bridge) allied <hi>Aſia</hi> to <hi>Europe.</hi> I ſhould never make an end if I ſhould commemorate how much Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108455:8"/> how much Hiſtorians, Poets, Kings, Cities, and Princes (whom we may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce out of the Monuments of Learning, as out of the Trojan Horſe) attribute to this Alliance, to this Love, to this Piety; but theſe things are obvious, and I will be more brief, eſpecially ſince in ſo plain a caſe, we need not alledge unneceſſary witneſſes. Yet the Chriſtian Inſtitution is not to be paſs'd by in ſilence, whoſe Dignity is deſervedly ſo great, that its Authority might prevail without the aid of Reaſon. According to the Inſtitutes hereof Marriages which are confirmed by Oath, Faith, and Iſſue, if they be performed as they were firſt commanded, will afterwards eaſily be allowed; which how approvable they are, Chriſt our Lord hath confirmed in the Goſpel, as well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he forbad to divorce a Wife, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe being invited he went to a Wedding. Of which things we muſt ſo think, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Marriages are not deſirable of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet, in my opinion, they are to be referred to that which is good in it ſelf. We purſue Wiſdom, Friendſhip, and Health for themſelves: We deſire Wit, Learning, Knowledge, and a comely agreeableneſs of Manners, conjugal Embraces, Meat, Drink, and Sleep, as neceſſary to the other. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:108455:8"/> we believe Marriages to be good, both for the ſake of iſſue and the Society of both Sexes, which Nature hath recommended wonderfully to us; otherwiſe among old People the Dignity of Wedlock would be extinguiſhed, if they either wanted Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or if they were deprived of the hopes of Propagation; in all which there is this great praiſe, that the lawfulneſs of Beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Iſſue ſecures Men from the turpitude of Incontinence; wherefore Man and Wife are united by that Law, by that Covenant, and by that Alliance that they may not be ſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by any ſeparation. Although at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent I ſeem to ſee ſome obſtructing me in the very entrance, who object the froward Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of <hi>Xantippe,</hi> and delight in the wit of that <hi>Laco,</hi> who when he had Married a Wife of great frowardneſs, and for that matter was calumniated, he ſaid to the Aſſertors, it is an ancient and excellent Proverb, That of Evils, if it may be, the leaſt is to be choſen. To which we anſwer many other things, and that of <hi>Socrates</hi> chiefly, who when he had brought home <hi>Euthidemus</hi> from the School, that he might join the Sacred Rite of Hoſpitality to his good Will; <hi>Xantippe</hi> being angry overthrew the Table. When <hi>Socrates</hi> underſtood this to be troubleſome to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:108455:9"/> his Gueſt, he ſaid, Be of good courage, we oftentimes endure more grievous things from tame Creatures, that we may receive far more inconſiderable Fruits, as Eggs and Chickens, than from a Wife. Hither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the Diſcourſe of that famous Perſon and Cenſor <hi>Metellus Numidicus,</hi> in which when he diſcourſed concerning Marriage, theſe things are commemorated to be ſaid by him; If we <hi>Romans</hi> could live without Wives, we ſhould be freed from that trouble; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Nature has ſo ordered it, that we can neither live commodiouſly with them, nor in any manner without them, we ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther provide for a perpetual happineſs than a ſhort pleaſure. But theſe things ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice concerning Wedlock, becauſe they are treated of more copiouſly by moſt Learned Men: But that we might handle the moſt neceſſary matters, we have collected theſe things. Now we will briefly explain the Wifes duty, laid open as it were to one view, which we never find digeſted into Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod by our Forefathers. Although before we enter that Point, we will direct what a Wife ought to be choſen; only we will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh this, that there ſhould be no excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Marriage ſo great, to which the Will of the Father ſhould not be preferr'd, even
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:108455:9"/> by the inſtruction of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> who when he was invited by <hi>Cyapares</hi> to take an excellent Woman with a large Portion of Gold, ſaid, That he would not accept the offer till he was aſſured that the Match was approved by his Parents.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. II. <hi>With what Qualifications and Manners a Wife ſhould be—choſen.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE Ancients, whoſe Authority is in much uſe for their great Learning, have thought that we ought to regard in a Wife, Age, Manners, Deſcent, Beauty and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; which things if we neglect we ſhall always bring diſgrace and trouble to our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and oftentimes affliction to our ſelves: but if we ſhall diligently obſerve them, we ſhall provide for our Domeſtick Praiſe, and our Dignity and perpetual Pleaſure. But Virtue ought chiefly to be conſidered, the Efficacy and Dignity whereof is ſuch, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108455:10"/> if there were a deficiency in other things, the Nuptials would be acceptable; but if the other things were enjoy'd, they would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly become moſt pleaſant: for Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Affairs which are committed to the care of the Wife cannot be well regulated, unleſs they be Managed, Governed, and Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Prudence, Care, and Induſtry of the Woman. Citizens are prone to imitate the Manners of their Kings, Souldiers of their Emperours, Children of their Parents, and Maids of their Miſtreſſes. <hi>Homer</hi> is a noble Witneſs to us, who relates that the chaſte Maids of <hi>Andromache</hi> ſeemed ſo go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned that they excelled and far tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Maids of <hi>Helena</hi> in Chaſtity, Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and Labour; therefore the Woman of whom we now ſpeak may eaſily rule her Maids, if ſhe can govern her ſelf. Neither do I approve them in this place who only ſearch after, and earneſtly deſire, ſuch admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable things, in a Wife which they would chuſe, that are ſcarce to be found in many Ages. We read and hear many things, we always judge them to be praiſe-worthy who, although inferiour, endeavour to follow the Example of thoſe who are moſt laudable in the practice of Virtue.</p>
                  <p>It is remembred that in the Olympick
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:108455:10"/> Games <hi>Philomena</hi> obtained the reward, not becauſe ſhe overcame the noble <hi>Glaucus</hi> that moſt famous Wreſtler, but becauſe ſhe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled the Champions of her Age in Virtue. So although the <hi>Porcia's, Cornelia's,</hi> and <hi>Panthia's,</hi> thoſe Lights of Female Glory, are acknowledged, not to be of our Age; yet if we diligently ſearch, we may find thoſe who may be ornamental, uſeful, and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to us. After what manner they may be diſcovered will be found eaſie upon ſearch. <hi>Marcus Cato</hi> the Conſul and Cenſor, when he was old, Married a Virgin, whoſe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I ſhall chiefly repeat, becauſe I acquieſce in his Narrations taken out of a <hi>Greek</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument, as in a pleaſant Inn. Therefore <hi>Marcus Cato</hi> being old, having often ſeen the Daughter of his Client <hi>Salonius,</hi> was wonderfully delighted with her Wit and Manners. <hi>Salonius</hi> the Scribe, as he was wont, came upon a time with <hi>Cato</hi> to the Court; as they were going <hi>Cato</hi> ſaid, O <hi>Salonius,</hi> I have found out a Husband for your Daughter, and I think that you will approve all things, unleſs his great age be an Obſtacle. After thoſe ſpeeches which are wont to be uſed in ſuch matters at the firſt meeting, <hi>Cato</hi> profeſſeth himſelf to be that old Man, and promiſeth that (as much as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:108455:11"/> was in his power) he would take his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Wife. Whereupon <hi>Salonius</hi> admired that the Virtue of his Daughter ſhould ſo much attract <hi>Cato</hi>'s eſteem, that he would take to Wife one meanly Born, into that Family which was adorned with conſulary and triumphal Trophies. What ſhould I ſay more? He Married his Daughter. <hi>M. Cato</hi> the Son, than whom none was better, if we credit his Father, nor excelled him in Piety, was much troubled, and begged his pardon if he had done any thing againſt his Father, which ſhould induce him to bring him a Mother-in-Law; but he having applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Manners of that Virgin, anſwered, that ſhe pleaſed him wonderfully well; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther O deareſt Son ſhould you think that it was done to bring you a Mother-in-Law, but that I might have many Children like you, and leave behind me the beſt Citizens of the Common-wealth. For this cauſe <hi>Piſiſtratus</hi> (as it's ſaid) took to Wife a Woman en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with ſingular modeſty, his Sons being adult and inſtructed in the Liberal Sciences; becauſe the eminent Piety of his Children daily enflamed his deſire of Begetting the like. It is apparent by the judgment of <hi>M. Cato</hi> (than which nothing can be more Grave) and of <hi>Piſiſtratus,</hi> how highly we
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:108455:11"/> ought to eſteem Manners. Our City is full of Examples of this kind, of which it ſhall ſuffice to inſtance in a few. <hi>Andreas Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> the Father of our Renowned <hi>Mark,</hi> a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Citizen, and of a moſt honourable Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, took <hi>Lucia Viaria</hi> to Wife; whoſe worth was ſo perſpicuous and known to him, that he brought her home from her moſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearing acquaintance, ſaying, That if he could gain her conſent, the Marriage ſhould be Celebrated between them without any conſideration of Money. Therefore neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting the Riches of others he Married her for Virtue and Goodneſs. This matter did correſpond with the judgment of that pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Perſon: For truly ſhe educated his Sons-in-Law with that Care and that Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety that nothing could be more advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, nothing more tranquil in Domeſtick Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. Many years after, that moſt famous Perſon and excellent Citizen <hi>Juſtus Contari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> imitated this <hi>Barbarus</hi> my Kinſman, for being certified of the moderation, modeſty, and ſingular beauty of <hi>Franciſcus Panthalion Barbus</hi> his Daughter, the Spectators being withdrawn, he firſt ſpake to her Father, and declared to him that his Daughter pleaſed him more and more, and that he earneſtly deſired to have her, although poor, to Wife,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:108455:12"/> if it might be with his approbation. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Panthalion,</hi> moſt excellent by Birth and great Learning, is pleaſed therewith, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires time of deliberation, he Summons, according to Cuſtome, his uſual Friends; the matter being declared, it was by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all judged happy, proſperous, and fortunate; and <hi>Juſtus</hi> being now ancient is adjudged deſerving of that moſt noble Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, though of a ſmall Portion, for ſo the ſtate of her Family required. I may call thoſe Marriages happy which are deſired and purſued for the ſplendor of Virtue, and continue inviolated with great faithfulneſs and love; for (that I may omit in this place her other Commendations) ſhe ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly and courteouſly treated the Children of his former Wife, that in her daily Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, many of her Sons-in-Law remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing of a Mother-in-Law in her, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Name. Above all things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as I would have you to obſerve, my deareſt <hi>Laurentius,</hi> let the Manners of your Wife pleaſe you, without which I do not underſtand what can be hoped for in Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Affairs. <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> being asked what the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> ſhould do, being conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, anſwered, If a prudent Emperour manage the matter, we may refer that to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:108455:12"/> our concern. What compoſes, regulates, and renders commendable the Family Affairs, but chiefly the diligence, frugality, and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Wife? As a Prince ſhall not well govern a City unleſs he be expert in the Common-Law, the Cuſtoms of his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, and the Publick Affairs. Neither can a Pilot, which is ignorant of the Marine Art, reduce a Ship into the Haven out of a cruel Storm. Neither ſhall a Charioteer which is unskilful in his Employment be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded. So neither can Domeſtick Affairs be rightly managed, unleſs the excellency of the Miſtreſs of the Family be a ſingular Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to the reſt. And even as Souldiers which have an excellent Commander are aſhamed to deſert that place which is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them; ſo Men and Maid-ſervants will not forſake that part of the Family con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, the Cuſtody of which is committed to them by a chaſte and prudent Miſtreſs. <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> that moſt Grave Philoſopher, in thoſe Books which he hath excellently written concerning the Commonwealth, hath inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted that Magiſtracies ſhould be beſtowed on the moſt excellent, not the moſt ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Citizens; for he foreſaw that in a ſhort time very few would ſtrive for it, if not thoſe who were well deſerving, but thoſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108455:13"/> who were ambitious Champions ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Dignity. Wherefore he propoſed a publick Reward to the Magiſtrates, leſt the damage which may accrew to their private Affairs, ſhould impede the publick Duties of the Commonwealth; for we ſhould ſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteem Prudence in a Wife (that if our fortunes will permit) we ſhould even neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect a Wifes Portion, or willingly be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with very little, that we may obtain Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick praiſe and peace. This very thing will bring us greater glory than if we had Wives adorned with Jewels and Gold, but void of Honeſty. A certain <hi>Ionian</hi> Woman when ſhe proudly boaſted of her Treaſures &amp; Riches, was thus anſwered by the Wife of <hi>Phocion, Phocion</hi> is my Riches &amp; Treaſure who hath been Prince of the <hi>Athenians</hi> now this twenty years, for his merits to his Country. After the ſame manner we may glory in the worth of a Wife, and pretermit them, who being enriched with the Wealth and Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a Wife are liable to innumerable trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. Theſe things are fading, but thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer firm and ſtable things do truly unite the minds of Married Perſons. <hi>Philip<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Alexander,</hi> whom <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth a King excellent in Fortune and Valour, fervently and wonderfully loved <hi>Theſſala</hi> to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:108455:13"/> that degree, that it was ſaid he was induced by Love-potions; wherefore <hi>Olympias</hi> uſed her utmoſt endeavour that <hi>Theſſala</hi> her ſelf might be brought into his power: whom when ſhe beheld adorn'd with a modeſt Countenance and Deportment, ſhe ſaid, The Calumnies avail little againſt you, for you bear the Inchantments of Love about you, and Love-potions are prepared by the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your goodneſs. What need I ſay more? Let us chuſe a Wife of good behaviour, whoſe Frugality joined to Honour, Profit, and Pleaſure may be eſteemed, delighted in, and loved by us.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Concerning the Age of a Wife to be choſen.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SInce I have already treated of the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of a Wife, which if ſhe be rightly educated, ſhe hath, or may eaſily obtain: I ſhall now briefly diſcourſe of her Age, thoſe things which have been handled and taught by <hi>Zachary</hi> and many Learned
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:108455:14"/> Perſons. But I think that this is firſt to be premoniſhed, that you chuſe a Virgin, not a Widow; a young, not an elderly Woman: for ſhe will more eaſily learn thoſe things which are neceſſary and commodious, and if ſhe hath contracted any Vices they may more ſpeedily be eradicated; For we can eaſily make impreſſions upon ſoft Wax, but we can ſcarce deface thoſe which are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd upon hard and ſolid. We may affix upon tender minds what inſtitutes we pleaſe. We can ſcarce with great ingeny, elaborate induſtry, and ſingular care, reduce Widows, formed both to their own and others hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, to our own cuſtomes: for who can hope to ſtraighten old Vines, which were at firſt crooked? Who will conceive that a young Man nouriſhed in <hi>Alexandrian</hi> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, will change his courſe of life to that of an abſtemious old Man? Who will think that he will be well qualified in old age, who in his youth was obſtinate, luſtful, auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and cruel? So Widows if they have imbibed any vicious habits, we may almoſt deſpair of reducing them to our courſe of life: Wherefore excellently, <hi>Timotheus,</hi> that noble Trumpeter, was wont to require a double reward from them, who formerly had received inſtructions from other Maſters of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:108455:14"/> that Art, and a ſingle one from them who were ignorant of that Art: for as theſe are to be taught, ſo thoſe are to be untaught before they are capable of inſtruction. To this refers that reaſon which is approved by uſe, and produced by Nature. For thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, who enquire exquiſitely into the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den cauſes of things, that Nature her ſelf intends that which is the beſt, and that when ſhe cannot produce a Male, ſhe conceives a Female, which is ennobled and perfected by the union of the Male; and therefore that Women love thoſe moſt to whom they are joined in the firſt congreſs. Why is it ſo? Becauſe a Virgin will more eaſily entertain good Manners, and renounce her depraved, and will love more ardently. Moreover the Marriages of Widows amongſt the <hi>Romans</hi> could not eſcape the imputation of levity and impudence, who alſo permitted a Divorce; but thoſe whom they obſerved to be content with one only Husband, they highly admired for their modeſty. Neither did they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud the Matrons of their due praiſe, who preſerved purely, and with a ſincere faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, their affections devoted to their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Husbands, although defunct. Who will not deſervedly condemn her of intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, whoſe fervent deſires are not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:108455:15"/> of an allay by the embraces of many Husbands? Who will not admire with great delight the chaſte <hi>Dido,</hi> who ſaid, He who firſt join'd me to himſelf, hath engroſs'd my love, he ſhall enjoy and poſſeſs it in his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre? Which none ſhould wonder at, ſince Crows and Turtles, by Natures inſtinct, when their Mates are dead, continue chaſte, and in a manner Widows.</p>
                  <p>I have expatiated too much, while I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the Marriages, and accuſe the Inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of Widows. Let us therefore return to the Subject of our Diſcourſe: It chiefly conduceth to Domeſtick Peace that a parity of diſpoſitions, and ſimilitude of deſires do unite Husbands and Wives, or retain them being united. For this reaſon prudent Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity together with <hi>Venus</hi> hath placed in the Temples <hi>Mercury</hi> and the Graces and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence; becauſe conformity of minds, concord and complaiſance claim to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a chief place in the duty of a Wife. Henceforth we are to treat at what time a Woman is Marriageable and of years a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapted to the Nuptial ſtate. <hi>Heſiod</hi> that moſt ancient Poet, and <hi>Xenophon</hi> that moſt ſweet Philoſopher have aſcribed the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth year to a Woman, the thirtieth to a Man; but <hi>Lycurgus</hi> hath appointed the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:108455:15"/> eighteenth year for Women, but the thirty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeventh for Men: chiefly accounting it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to Poſterity in the propagation whereof he did not ſo much regard the number as the ſtrength. In this place (O moſt pleaſant <hi>Laurentius)</hi> I deſire thee to give me leave to digreſs freely, which I know will not be unpleaſant to thee. For this cauſe therefore he appointed, that his Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens ſhould not lodge with their Wives in the ſame Beds; but that they ſhould pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately join embraces with them in the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, that they being reſtrained from a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual and (as I may ſo ſay) unlimited congreſs, they might take care of their health, and that their Children might be more ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſt. For that moſt prudent Perſon fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw, that mortals were apt to delight in fond ſenſual pleaſures, from the allurements whereof he hoped for the greateſt part to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his Citizens by reſtraining them from a continual volupty. To this matter the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Diſcipline much contributed, for he took care by many Sports and Games that the Wives Dignity might not incur any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace by ſloth or idleneſs; for he appointed a School of Running, Shooting, Diſcipline, and of Wreſtling for the <hi>Spartane</hi> Women, that they being frequently exerciſed therein,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:108455:16"/> their Sons and Daughters might obtain a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ſtrength from their Parents. He alſo declared that he was therefore the Author of that Law, that the <hi>Spartane</hi> Women might more undauntedly endure the pains of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, and if at any time any contention aroſe they might fight couragiouſly for their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. I ſuppoſe &amp; conjecture that theſe years of Marriage were limited by him that as much as could be the weakneſs of that Sex might be defended from the ſnares of pleaſures: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it came to paſs, that the <hi>Laconian</hi> Women greatly excell'd as in all kind of glory, ſo eſpecially in modeſty. The moſt noble an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of <hi>Geradata</hi> the <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> is a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Teſtimony hereof, whom when <hi>Xen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> asked, what puniſhment by the Laws of <hi>Lycurgus</hi> were inflicted upon Adulterers, he anſwered, That <hi>Lycurgus</hi> had not enacted any thing concerning them; ſince it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent that we have not one Adulterer amongſt us; neither, O <hi>Xentus,</hi> would I have thee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire at it ſince amongſt us Luxury, Riches, Ornaments, and the other allurements of Pleaſure are diſeſteemed; but Frugality, Modeſty, and Chaſtity cannot be ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applauded. In which Laws the <hi>Spartan</hi> Women being born and educated, they alone ſeemed to bring forth not only Men, but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:108455:16"/> excellent Perſons, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> it is reported that <hi>Gorgon</hi> the Wife of <hi>Leonides</hi> did aſſert. For when a certain Gueſt of her Husband bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> Women becauſe (unlike to others) they ruled their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, <hi>Gorgon</hi> ſaid, I confeſs it, neither do we wrong them therein, becauſe we alone bring forth excellent Men. But perchance I have inſiſted longer on theſe things than is needful. I think it unneceſſary now to pronounce a definitive Sentence which of theſe Opinions is the true. Truly in the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of a prudent Judge each defends it ſelf. For neither (as I hope) do you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of me that I ſhould preſcribe certain Laws, as it were, framed by inevitable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity (as they ſay by Parliamentary Rolls) concerning Wives; but I will chiefly inſiſt upon thoſe things which I find approved ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by precept or uſe; yet we allow that moſt of theſe things may be changed by the cauſes, times and conjunctures of things: for Judgment and Prudence (which the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients defined to be the Production of Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and Memory) are neceſſary for us. Since therefore we have already treated of the Age of a Wife, in the next place we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to diſcourſe of her Nobility, upon which we ſhall inſiſt more largely.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:108455:17"/>
                  <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Concerning the Nobility of a Wife—to be choſen.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Wiſh (O dear <hi>Laurentius)</hi> the Matter would ſuffer to ſpeak all I can excogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate concerning Deſcent it ſelf; I could more abundantly evidence (as I ſuppoſe) that the Arms of our Anceſtours ought to be more eſteemed than that Cuſtome will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit which now daily grows more and more in uſe among us. Yet for the preſent we ſhall relate ſome things which ſeem moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious and excellent, other things per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>haps we ſhall handle more largely hereafter: Therefore I intend to begin herein from Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelf. A Paſture flouriſhing, Planted and Sown Field does greatly aſſure us, that for the ſake of our Poſterity we ſhould cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the Nuptial Rites with Women nobly born. Seeds are reduced into their proper origins; and we find that thoſe are the beſt Crops which are produc'd by the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Corn; and we know that very many, and thoſe the beſt ſorts of Berries, Nuts and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:108455:17"/> Shrubs, will not grow but in their proper and fertile Soils; and if they be tranſplanted to a more barren Soil they loſe their Natural Virtue, and Apples loſing their former juice degenerate: alſo excellent Ciens if they be Ingrafted in bad Stocks, bear worſe Fruits. Which is alſo incident to Men themſelves, that they expect far more Illuſtrious Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from Noble Women. Hence chiefly we diſcern in them the repreſentations of their Mothers bodies and minds (as we ſee in moſt Children) and it is certain that a Woman is of great concern in the Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Children. For as ſome judicious Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians aſſert, that a Female is chiefly procre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated by the Woman. It is very noble that the Civil Law allows Children to enjoy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour from their Mothers; for (as it is inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by the <hi>Roman</hi> Laws) it is certain that all thoſe were accounted free born, who had Noble Mothers, although their Fathers were Slaves: which alſo we obſerve that the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givers of the <hi>Lycians</hi> enacted, among whom if any Noble Woman Married an Ignoble Servant, yet the Children begotten of her were Noble. Poets teſtifie this to us, who affirm that thoſe who have a Goddeſs for their Mother are Divine. We ſhould want time, if we ſhould enumerate particulars;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:108455:18"/> but <hi>Aeneas, Achilles,</hi> and <hi>Orpheus</hi> chiefly for this reaſon are accounted Deities. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther does the Nobleneſs of the Mother avail only to the procreation, but much to the education of the Children: who is ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that he doth not perceive that this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is of great importance to them that are born? For the choiceſt Seeds being Sown (that we may uſe an Analogy of the ſame kind) unleſs the Field be Tilled with great care and induſtry, the Corn will be obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to many hazards. No body can doubt that any thing is more eſteemed by renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Women than that the honour of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents may be more and more illuſtrated by the ſplendor of the Children: of whom un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs there be diligent care taken they will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeem infamous in Vice than noble in Extraction. Moreover the dignity and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Anceſtors often cauſeth that the Poſterity is, and is accounted worthy of the greateſt honours: alſo let them rely upon their own Virtues, as they are obliged by the Laws of Nature; for unleſs that their Virtues be evident in them, they will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive themſelves degenerate with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt contumelies of all Men. And as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of former glory incites Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers accuſtomed to triumphs to be valiant
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:108455:18"/> and ardent; ſo the remembrance of Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Renown will ſtimulate them who were before ſpontaneouſly earneſt in the purſuit thereof. They have an eaſie paſſage to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour who are of noble deſcent. Who is not aſſur'd (ſo that they be not excell'd in worth in other things) that thoſe ſhould be preferr'd before mean Perſons by the Suffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of all? Who is ignorant, that although they are unworthy of honour by their own merits, yet oftentimes many things are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded to them for the ſake of thoſe moſt worthy Perſons their Anceſtors? We read of many who would die for their Country, both that they might perform their duty, and leave a large Patrimony to their Children with the Memory of their Name: for at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> their Children were maintained at the publick charge, who died for their Country. At <hi>Rome</hi> a pedeſtral Statue was appointed to be erected in the Market-place, for them who died in Embaſſage (if that Office cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their death) that it might be a Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their honourable death, and add a luſtre to their Children for ever. Amongſt us if in the troubleſome and perilous times of our republick, the earneſt deſire, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and vigilance of any is evident, they are rewarded according to their deſerts, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:108455:19"/> with power, or riches, or honour, and not they alone, but alſo their Children and Poſterity. On ſome a City, and the moſt honourable eſteem in that City is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd. Theſe things are ſpoken for this cauſe that it may be apparent that Parents ſhould be advantagious and ornamental to their Children. Neither would I have this to be underſtood as ſpoken of Fathers on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but alſo of Mothers; whoſe Virtue and Merit have oftentimes obtained much Renown for their Children with Poſterity. But the misfortune of an Ignoble Birth hath been ſo adverſe to many, that they could neither attain the ſtate of Nobility, nor from the obſcurity of their Anceſtors appear in luſtre. For the envy of others is always an obſtacle to the advancements of mean Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Dogs (as the Proverb relates) although they bark and are fierce againſt ſtrangers, yet are tractable to the Domeſticks. Therefore we are to retain the dignity of our Parents, and communicate it to our Children; which when other things are uncertain, fading, and tranſitory, being firmly Rooted, can by no force be ſubverted nor overthrown. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet therefore do I approve their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who being meanly born, endeavour to obtain moſt Noble Wives. We may moſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:108455:19"/> aptly compare thoſe Perſons to them, who when they cannot mount upon the tall Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels, teach them after the <hi>Syrian</hi> manner to kneel and lye down; for ſuch Perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing incapable of advancement, render the women more debaſed. Therefore we will chiefly approve thoſe Marriages, whereby we being made more honourable, ſhall ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our Children more eminent and potent. VVhence that ancient <hi>Roman</hi> Cuſtome is thought to ariſe, whereby it is prohibited to marry wives related to them, leſt the love whereto we are obliged by the right of this relation ſhould be confin'd in narrow bounds, and ſhould in a manner deprive Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity of much Felicity, which might be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by other affinities: hither refers that union of friendſhip, whereby a City is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted by theſe kinds of amities, as by ſome certainties. But <hi>Claudius Nero,</hi> that Plague and Peſtilence of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted a Decree from the Senate, whereby it was enacted, that the marriages of Uncles and Neeces were lawful, that he might maintain his unruly and unbridled Luxury, by publick Authority: Yet there were none of any rank did pollute themſelves with this inceſt, except one <hi>Callidius Severus,</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Knight, whom yet, very many moſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:108455:20"/> noble Authors did aſſert, was allur'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto for the ſake of <hi>Agrippina.</hi> Therefore (as you O <hi>Laurentius</hi> have already excellently done) let us chuſe noble wives, that our Society may be more pleaſant, and having Children more noble by Nature and Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that we may fortifie them who are pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing glory, abundantly with honour and power, by our Domeſtick Examples: For eminent Perſons will vigilantly remember, always conſider, and be mindful of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and to reſtore carefully and entirely their dignity, as an Inheritance, which they have received not from their Father only, but alſo from their Mother, to their Children.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Concerning the Beauty of a Wife to be choſen.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>NOW here we ſhall enter upon that part with which others are wont to begin who omitted the former: we ſhall now treat concerning Beauty, which (as many think) conſiſts in the Compoſure of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:108455:20"/> the Body, and chiefly in the amiableneſs of the Hair, Eyes, Face, Neck, and Hands. I think women of a low ſtature (although the Compoſure of the Body be proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able) are rather adapted to unlawful vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial pleaſures than the function of a wife, for they ſeem rather accommodated to thoſe delights, than the dignity of propagating Iſſue. Wherefore at <hi>Lacedemon</hi> the Ephori fin'd <hi>Archidamus</hi> their King in a great ſum of money, becauſe he married a wife of a ſmall ſtature; thinking that his ſurviving Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue would be Children not Kings. And (leſt my diſcourſe ſhould be more prolix in its other parts) the Hair is ſo comely in a woman, that it incited <hi>Homer</hi> often to term <hi>Hellen</hi> her ſelf beautiful from this one Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of her Hair. And doth not our <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil,</hi> when he deſcribes a wiſe Perſon, and would in few words ſtile him beautiful, add this part of decency, ſaying, his Face and Shoulders were like unto the Gods? for the Goddeſs favour'd her Son with a comely Head of Hair and beſtow'd a bright Eye upon his youth, and honours delightful to it. Believe me (O <hi>Laurentius)</hi> if <hi>Mars</hi> had beheld <hi>Venus</hi> ſhaven, that ardour, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with that moſt warlike God was poſſeſſed, had forthwith vaniſhed, ſo that he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:108455:21"/> been enſnared by the arts of <hi>Vulcan.</hi> A certain Citizen of thine (whom for the ſake of his honour I name not) aſcribes either the only, or the greateſt excellency of a wife to this beauty whereof I now diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. But as I will not deprive this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of its praiſe, ſo I cannot concede the greateſt to it; whoſe power truly is ſuch that it hath and may overcome the Victours of all Nations. <hi>Jupiter</hi> himſelf, who by the Suffrages of the Poets is termed the Father of Gods and Men, hath often appeared in the likeneſs of a Shower, a Swan, and manifold appearances, that he might enjoy that beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by which he was captivated: but I ſhall ſay nothing of the others, whom the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude have made Gods, over whom (as <hi>Anacreon</hi> ſaith) <hi>Cupid</hi> triumpheth. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity teſtifieth to us, that very many are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to be immortal for the only excellency of their beauty. Moreover <hi>Paris</hi> himſelf contemned the Empire of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and the victory in wars, that he might obtain <hi>Hellen,</hi> whom he eſteemed moſt beautiful, when he beheld the Goddeſs <hi>Juno, Minerva</hi> and <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> moſt earneſtly contending concerning the luſtre of beauty, and which were moſt excellent in his judgment: Alſo it is a great moſt amiable thing that this beauty ſeems a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:108455:21"/> certain Divine things and moſt worthy of great honours. VVho is ſo void of huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity that Beauty it ſelf may not delight him? Almoſt all Men love beautiful Perſons, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem them worthy to govern, and moſt willingly obey them; therefore moſt aptly that moſt prudent Poet <hi>Virgil,</hi> ſaith, Virtue ſeated in a fair Body is more acceptable and advantagious. For although Virtue be not more eſtimable, yet (I know not how) it is more pleaſing. The Multitude rather reveres than loves valiant, wiſe, and juſt Perſons, if they be deformed: whence, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, <hi>Plato</hi> was wont to adviſe <hi>Xenocrates</hi> (who was remarkably deformed in Body) that he ſhould often do good things ſponta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neouſly; for his Wiſdome, being joined to his deformed Body, was unpleaſant to very many, and of it ſelf very dear to few. But wherefore ſhould I rehearſe ſo many of theſe things? that we may rather chuſe to live with handſome Wives (for whom many would die:) Neither do I rehearſe this for the ſake of pleaſure (which is repell'd by a great and ſober mind, as a Wave by a Stone) but I think it meet to be referr'd to the Propagation of Iſſue, and the pleaſant Society of each others life. <hi>Juno</hi> hath wiſely aſſerted it in <hi>Virgil,</hi> when ſhe thus en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:108455:22"/> to perſwade <hi>Aeolus,</hi> even with the hope of a reward: I have fourteen hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Nymphs, whereof I will Marry you to <hi>Deiope</hi> the faireſt, and ſhe ſhall be yours, that ſhe may all her days live with you in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe of ſuch merits, and make you a Father of a fair Offspring. In which place it may eaſily be obſerved (unleſs the Tale be told to a deaf Man) wherefore we ought greatly to eſteem handſome Wives. But I perceive that, in the earneſtneſs of ſpeaking, I have farther expatiated than the Matter it ſelf did require; wherefore I ſhall deſiſt, and now approach nearer to our purpoſe. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though above I have written many things concerning Beauty, yet I would ſo be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that I highly value it, if it be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with good manners, and other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies; but ſeparated from theſe, I do by no means approve it: for as Fire that is eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kindled of Straw, will ſuddenly be extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, unleſs more durable Fuel be added thereto; ſo the love between Husband and Wife, proceeding from the Beauty of the Body, will ſuddenly vaniſh, unleſs the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown of Ingeny, compoſure of manners and holineſs of life, correſpond thereto. When it was reported to <hi>Olympias,</hi> that one of the Royal Family had Married a Wife,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:108455:22"/> who, it was ſaid, ſeemed moſt fair, but was of ill report, ſhe ſaid; This young Man, if he had oftner conſulted with thoſe prudent Perſons his Anceſtors, than with himſelf, he would not have Married a Wife ſolely by the guidance of his Eyes: for this Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Beauty deſerves no praiſe, nor no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, unleſs a firm and expreſs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Virtue be annexed to it: which <hi>Homer,</hi> that moſt great Philoſopher, and Poet, plainly evidenceth, who once reported, that <hi>Nireus</hi> (the faireſt of all the <hi>Greeks, Achilles</hi> only excepted) came, together with others, to <hi>Aulis,</hi> after which he is in no place remembred: for truly he brought no valour to <hi>Troy,</hi> the proper reward of which is glory, whereby <hi>Homer</hi> determined for ever to adorn thoſe Half-Gods. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can Beauty only cauſe love to Wives, but alſo to unchaſte Women: concerning which I remember that of one <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dua;</hi> He being the Son of a rich and noble Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, fervently loved a wanton Woman of extraordinary Beauty, from whoſe love he could not be withdrawn by the authority and kindneſs of his Father; when his Father ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved theſe things, with the great hazard of his Sons reputation, he reſolved to apply a Remedy to his Diſtemper; he hires that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:108455:23"/> mercenary unchaſte Woman, addicted to venereal pleaſures, keeps her at home with his Son; the wretched young man lodges with her, embraces her, and for ſome daies injoyes that ſenſual pleaſure, which he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the chief and only good: not long after when ſatiety began to aſſwage his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful love, and he began to diſdain her with a greater freedom, that which he was wont to love ſo ardently in her, he deſpiſeth, and by little and little the youth recovered and was freed, by the care of his Father, from that cruel and furious diſtemper. What happineſs can we expect in a Wife, if beauty alone ſhall attract our affections to her, to whom worth and the ſociety of a comfortable life ſhould unite us? Truly we can hope for no better ſucceſs, than <hi>Menelaus</hi> had with <hi>Helen;</hi> or (if we obſerve fables) <hi>Vulcan</hi> with <hi>Venus,</hi> or <hi>Minos</hi> with <hi>Paſiphae,</hi> or <hi>Theſeus</hi> with <hi>Phaedra,</hi> or (that I may look homeward) <hi>Claudius Caeſar</hi> with <hi>Meſſalina.</hi> But why ſhould I with many words, ſo long inſiſt upon theſe things, as concerning obſcure matters? let us love fair Wives (if they be correſpondent in other things) that the Nuptials may be delightful to us, honourable and advantageous to our Poſterity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:108455:23"/>
                  <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Concerning the Riches of a Wife to be choſen.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Have ſufficiently diſcourſed concerning Manners, Age, Extraction, and Beauty; furthermore, according to our purpoſe, we ſhall ſpeak a few things which ſeem not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent to this matter, concerning Riches, which is the remaining part to be treated of in the choice of a Wife. Since therefore we purſue all things which appertain to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Ornament of Wedlock, and to the plenty, wealth, riches, and conveniences of life, we muſt be careful of our honour and profit, which produce gratitude, liberality, and magnificence; in which truly the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſplendour of Vertue conſiſts: Although we may be liberal by the inclinations of a grateful mind, yet (even as Emperours, Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and Phyſicians) we ſhall not ſeem high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly praiſe-worthy, unleſs we manifeſt our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires by our actions: Wherefore Riches are uſeful for many things; for we may give to every one according to their deſert, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:108455:24"/> much upon our Neighbours and Friends, whereby we ſhall fortifie our Children with the riches, aſſiſtance, and love of thoſe to whom we have been liberal, for Parents are remarked and loved in their Children; and no duty ſhould ſeem more honourable than Gratitude, wherein whoever is voluntarily deficient, he muſt neceſſarily be impious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the immortal God, his Country, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, Kindred, and Friends; finally he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends againſt all thoſe by whoſe bounty he being obliged, is neither thankful to them, nor remunerates them. Whence, very nobly, by the <hi>Perſian</hi> Laws ingrateful Perſons were ſeverely puniſhed; for (as <hi>Herodotus</hi> relates) they accounted it the greateſt fault to lye, but the next, to be indebted. Why not? They rightly conceived, that he who was not aſhamed to owe to another, would both often erre againſt the duty of a good man in many things, and deceive him, and lye moſt often: Therefore we ſhould ſo highly value Riches, which although we our ſelves have little need of, yet the moſt honourable uſe thereof moſt largely extends to our Friends, and to all ſorts of Perſons. <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> ſent a great deal of Gold to that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent perſon <hi>Phocion;</hi> that moſt ſevere and moſt conſtant perſon refuſed the Gift, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:108455:24"/> he had no need of that Money: After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he was asked, whether he had no Friends, whom the ſociety of their moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Studies and ſimilitude of life had joined to himſelf? it being moſt equitable that he ſhould be bountiful and liberal to them: but you may ſee (O <hi>Phocion)</hi> what you have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined of your ſelf. Indeed the almoſt incredible Riches of <hi>Darius</hi> ſcarce ſufficed <hi>Alexander</hi> liberally to relieve their Fortunes whoſe worth was dear to him. This will be a great advantage to your Children, that (which ſhould be eſteemed moſt noble) ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous young men ſhould be inſtructed and taught excellent Studies and Arts; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with being endued, they may become Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren worthy of thoſe renowned Perſons their Parents, and may render their Anceſtors more illuſtrious: (Which ſince it is ſo) we muſt be diligently careful of our wealth, leſt we be judged and thought, by them who envy us, to have ill provided for our Profit and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. But as if Wine be mingled with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and if there be the greater part and por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Water than of the Wine, yet we call it Wine; ſo we term Plenty and Riches the Husbands not the Wives, although the woman brought the greater and more valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part thereof; although I think he moſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:108455:25"/> conſults his own intereſt, not who accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates the moſt to, but who makes the beſt proviſion for his Family concerns.</p>
                  <p>Moreover (as the Phyſicians aſſert) it is neceſſary to our perfect health, that moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture be diſperſed through all the parts of the body: ſo we inſtruct them who marry that they ſhould unite not Money (whereof we ſpeak) but Minds and Friends and mutual Relations one to another: wherefore it was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacted by the Roman Laws that the Man and Wife ſhould not receive any Gifts of each other, that they might be aſſured that nothing was peculiar, but all things common to each other, whereby the domeſtick Affairs might be managed with a greater care, diligence, and faithfulneſs. That of <hi>Dion</hi> to <hi>Dionyſius</hi> is true, Every one is more diligent in his own than in others concerns. Whence wiſely Princes are wonted to be admoniſhed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that their Cities are their Houſes, their Citizens their Children, and themſelves the Prefects of their Family, that they may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the ſafety and welfare of thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns over which they preſide, by care, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, induſtry, and vigilance, and deſire their felicity. But of theſe things hitherto. I would our Age had happened in that time, in which Youth had been to be taught, not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:108455:25"/> untaught, that it ſhould not greatly eſteem Riches and Money in Wedlock; truly the ſociety and union of men had been beſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved: But the moſt, even from their infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, are ſo inclined and inſtructed to a vain hope of lucre, that they will omit nothing which they can endeavour or perform by la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and perils, that they think can contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to this their ſervile avarice. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I reſolved not to incite nor inflame the Youth of our Age highly to value Riches with Wives, but rather to exhort them (if their Eſtates will permit) to deliberate hereof (even as I have written) after all other things. I fear I have offended very many, but yet I will ſpeak what I think. I cannot enough blame thoſe, who by how much the richer they are, ſo much more earneſtly they affect Wives, who are capable of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs than the duty of a wife: for as Looking-Glaſſes embelliſhed with Gold and Pearls are unuſeful to us, unleſs they pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray a like repreſentation; ſo furthermore I think the Riches of the wife unprofitable, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Pattern of her Husbands Diſcipline ſhall appear eaſie to her, even in penury it ſelf. <hi>Alexander</hi> is applauded, becauſe he took to wife <hi>Barſines</hi> (as ſome ſay) of whom he begat <hi>Hercules,</hi> the modeſt Daughter of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:108455:26"/> 
                     <hi>Artabazus,</hi> ſprung of a Royal Family, learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Greek Letters, although poor; great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contemning the Nuptials of <hi>Darius</hi>'s Daughter with an infinite maſs of Gold. There were many, both Princes and private Perſons, who were and are accounted great, as well in other things, as in the deſpiſing of Wives Portions, with whoſe Praiſes, as with Stars, Hiſtory is reſplendent. But no ſatiety of Poſſeſſions, or Tenements, or precious Houſhold Stuff can ſatisfie thoſe above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Perſons; and in the midſt of much riches they are poor; they covet richer not worthier Matches. And as perſons unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of Horſemanſhip highly value Horſes with ſplendid Reins, and perſons unskill'd in Military Affairs Golden Helmets, and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>literate men depraved Books with moſt adorned Boſſes; ſo many wiſh for Wives with full Purſes. My moſt learned and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant <hi>Guarinus</hi> was wont rightly to compare them to ſtately Sepulchres: For in them, whereas their appearance is moſt ſplendid, joined with various Ornaments, within there is nothing comely, but great filthineſs, turpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and corruption, and many things which are the products of death. <hi>Aeſop</hi> that moſt ancient <hi>Phrygian</hi> Writer (in whoſe Fable a ſingular gravity is joined to an equal courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie)
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:108455:26"/> in a manner ingeniouſly profeſſeth to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe us herein, who relates that a Fox en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into the Shop of a certain Muſician, found a Harp, the top whereof was the Head of a man faſhioned wonderfully with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geny, Art, induſtry, Jewels, and Gold, which when he had leiſurely admired, he ſaid, This is a rich H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad, but it has no brains. We may ſay the ſame of the richeſt women, unleſs they be ſufficiently fit to perform the duty of a Wife.</p>
                  <p>That raſh <hi>Paris</hi> enjoyed the rich <hi>Hellen:</hi> The moſt prudent <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> eſpouſed the chaſt <hi>Penelope,</hi> than whom none of her time was more chaſte, none more modeſt: Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty admired, loved, and moſt highly extoll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this marriage; on the contrary, it has ſtigmatized the other to the memory of poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, with moſt grievous ignominies, even as that which was the Firebrand, Deſolation, Plague, and deſtruction of <hi>Aſia:</hi> It is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident that it happened becauſe he ſought helps and aſſiſtances of his unlawful paſſion. Wherefore <hi>Lycurgus</hi> prudently ordained that Wives ſhould be eſpouſed without portions, that the <hi>Spartan</hi> women might not remain unmarried for their Poverty, nor be married for their Riches; for ſo he foreſaw that the <hi>Spartanes</hi> would ſeek virtue not riches in
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:108455:27"/> Wives, and that the women would be far more diligent in the acquiſition of virtues: which that it might more eaſily be effected, thoſe former half-Gods (placed as in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain watch Tower, that they might afar off provide for poſterity) decreed not (as in this age) that women ſhould bring a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to their Husbands, but they dowries to their Wives, leſt their husbands ſhould covet their wealth, but that they might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider more diligently to whom they were to communicate themſelves, their children, and all their concerns: this above named Law (unleſs Cuſtom hath changed our minds, and pleaſures have by degrees rendered us effeminate) is to be renew'd, and not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main any longer repealed: for if we rent Lands and hire Servants that we may mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally profit them, who are advantageous to us; why ſhall we not judge that we ſhould do the ſame with wives, from whom we expect ſo neceſſary, ſo ſweet fruits? But unleſs we be firſt freed from pleaſures (thoſe alluring inducements) and precious orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Garments fit for luxurious perſons, and other unneceſſary things, neceſſity it ſelf, and that covetouſneſs which is reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed within no bounds be removed, we ſhall never deliberate ſeriouſly and freely of a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:108455:27"/> Wife: which ſince it is moſt evident I will inſiſt no longer upon in this place: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our youth ſhould recollect themſelves, and conſider more cautiouſly than covetouſly (even by your example) of their Marriages, leſt for the hope of lucre, or the ſake of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining gain, making themſelves the ſlaves of a portion, they kindle a domeſtick Flame, which they cannot eaſily extinguiſh. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (in my judgment) if they would do what may conduce to the benefit of them and theirs, let them chuſe Wives endued with Virtue, Age, Beauty, and Riches; of which things, if any thing be diſputable, we will ere long declare which ſhould be prefer'd; but firſt, which ſeems the beſt and alſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, we will a little confute ſome things.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Concerning the importance of time, and of other things to change our purpoſes.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>PErchance ſome will ſay what do you do? Who having undertaken to give pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:108455:28"/> concerning the chocie of a Wife, ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit mean and poor men, that you inſtruct onely fortunate perſons? To this I may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily anſwer, that I earneſtly wiſh, that theſe our ſhort commentaries may be common and uſeful to all; but if any either by the misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of their extraction or penury, are not in a capacity to make uſe of our advice, let them blame their fortune not our precepts: let us therefore return to our purpoſe. I ſeem to ſee ſome who although they may concur with me, that all thoſe requiſites whereof I have diſputed ſhould be chiefly regarded, yet they may object that thoſe things are rather to be wiſhed than hoped for: wherefore they will more earneſtly require me to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce this compariſon; neither can they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that all ſhould be <hi>Laurentius's,</hi> moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in the endowments of Mind, Body, and Fortune, to whom Wives of all ranks and of all degrees are offered; but I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that I have ſufficiently anſwered theſe perſons, by thoſe things which are before ſaid, when I above diſcourſed what I moſt eſteemed; of other things we ſhall treat hereafter: yet oftentimes there happen many cauſes either of time or neceſſity or occaſion; for which (as learned men ſay) we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to change our precepts. For we ought
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:108455:28"/> to conſult with time (as <hi>Pericles</hi> adviſeth <hi>Colmides,</hi> that moſt prudent councellor:) for as the Woers of <hi>Penelope</hi> deſpairing of her embraces freely and voluntarily enjoyed her Maids, ſo if we cannot obtain them who in every reſpect are moſt excellent, let us ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce with thoſe who are ſuitable to our dignities. Neither ſhould we imitate chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren who make ſport for the ſpectators by putting on their Parents Shoes: So they will ſeem ridiculous, who being mean and abject, induſtriouſly ſeek for wives in whom every proportion of an abſolute and perfect renown is obſerved. Therefore I admoniſh them, that they be not like to <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels with the great deriſion of all men; for when in a Council of Beaſts they deſired the Horns of a Hart, their Ears were almoſt plucked off, that thoſe who remain'd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent within their bounds might be an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to them. Therefore let our young men marry wives according to their abilities. The misfortunes of others may ſufficiently ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh them; let them take heed, leſt they themſelves become Examples to others. Wherefore we judge that Proverb, as well uſeful to many things, as chiefly appoſite to this; <hi>Like beſt accords with like.</hi> For what is more equal? what is more convenient?
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:108455:29"/> what is more facil? what is more eaſie, than to chuſe a wife ſuitable to themſelves? But I do not aſſent to them, to whom nothing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears more equal, than inequality it ſelf. Moreover we muſt have a regard to her Manners, to which we always concede the preference in this matter: For if her Genins incline her to other things, without vertue, or a propenſity to good manners, I ſhall not therefore applaud it. <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Orator being asked what was the chief thing in Eloquence, anſwered Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation; he alſo aſſigned the ſecond and third place to it, that he might more eaſily manifeſt, that as to the perſwaſive part the precedency is to be chiefly yielded to it. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther refers that grave witneſs <hi>Hortenſius,</hi> who being inferior to many in other things, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to have excelled almoſt all in Oratory. What <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> attributes to pronuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Oratory, we may aſcribe to Vertue it ſelf in a wife. Wherefore let us chiefly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard good manners which we have placed in the firſt rank, becauſe without theſe, Marriages cannot be rightly approved; in which above all things obedience, courteſie, and compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance ſhould be conſidered, that there may be no differences, nor divorces, nor finally no need of the appeaſing Goddeſs.</p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:108455:29"/>
                  <p> A certain <hi>Roman</hi> divorced a noble, rich, and beautiful Wife, at which all admired, and complained of him; to whom when he would approve his judgment, he ſaid, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Shoo, This in appearance is fair and new; but where it hurts me none knows beſides my ſelf. Therefore I would have Husbands not ſo much eſteem Portion, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, and Beauty, as Virtue and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of Diſpoſition in a Wife, to whom nothing ſhould be more eſtimable than the will of her Husband; but if with Nobility a Virgin ſhall preſerve approved manners, we ſhall the leſs need the Ornament of Beauty. <hi>Socrates</hi> exhorted young Men to behold themſelves in a Looking-glaſs, for ſo if they beheld themſelves deformed they might ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der themſelves fair and acceptable by Virtue: but if beautiful, to take heed leſt they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted that endowment of Nature by their wickedneſs. So I adviſe Husbands, if they have not handſome Wives, to think it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for them, that they are undoubtedly fair in Chaſtity, Age, and Nobility: let them conſent to the opinion of <hi>Gorgias,</hi> who afferted that the renown of the Wife, not the favour of Fortune ought to be regarded; but if they be beautiful, let them be ſo much dearer to them. If they excell in other
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:108455:30"/> things, but are poor or indigent, their Nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials will not be diſapproved even by the Example of <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> that moſt excellent King, for he preferred <hi>Cryſeides</hi> the Captive before <hi>Clytemneſtra</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> eſteeming her Superiour in Stature, Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Prudence, and laſtly in many Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Who ever covets to accumulate Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, will find himſelf to be in an errour, and ſhould think that he had better eſpouſe a good Wife, than a rich. <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies this unto us, who being asked by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Father whether he ſhould Marry his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Daughter to a good Man, but poor, or to one diſhoneſt, but rich? he anſwered, I had much rather you ſhould have a Son-in-Law who wanteth Riches, than Riches without the Man. That which that Prince of <hi>Greece</hi> inſtructed concerning Husbands, we give in Precept concerning Wives; for it is fit that we chuſe to our ſelves Wives, not Riches for our Wives. Wherefore (the <hi>Ephori</hi> being Judges) thoſe <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> were deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly puniſhed, who promiſed <hi>(Lyſander</hi> being living) to Marry his Daughters, but after his death they refuſed it; for although they Courted them when rich, they mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted their contempt of them being poor, although well educated. What ſhall I ſay
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:108455:30"/> more? My opinion is, that we ſhould do our endeavour to be united to thoſe Women, who may be in all reſpects honourable, dear, and pleaſant to us. For if it ſhall come into debate, let us be careful to Steer our Courſe in every particular according to the dignity of each Perſon, and (as <hi>Automedon</hi> and other Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Horſe affirm) we call thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and good Horſes, in which more things may be approved than diſapproved; ſo we may eſteem thoſe Women worthy of the praiſe of good Wives, in whom we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive either the moſt or the chief of theſe things, whereof we have diſcourſed. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may I impoſe ſuch an Obſtacle eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally upon the Men of our Age (for it would be a hard, and almoſt endleſs thing, although that I may wiſh and deſire it) as to reſtrain them from demanding all things, but they ſhould chiefly ſearch for Virtue: and with it they may aſſure themſelves that they may obtain all things, upon which I intend no longer to particularize; for the reſt are obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and will eaſily be demonſtrated by Wit and Prudence.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:108455:31"/>
                  <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Concerning Nuptial Solemnities.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT remains that I now ſpeak concerning the Marriage Rites, in which all things are ſo pleaſant, ſo amiable, lovely, and in every reſpect ſo delightful to our knowledge, that being hurried away by the vehemency of diſcourſe, I had almoſt omitted this one thing which was chiefly neceſſary to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. I ſhall (before I proceed to the other part) briefly recite a few things concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Marriages themſelves, which being now obſolete, and in a manner forgotten, I ſhall dig out of the Monuments of Antiquity; for it conduceth much to the matter concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which we now treat to ponder diligently in our minds, what thoſe ancient wiſe Men thought concerning the pomp and ſplendour of Marriages, whom even herein we ſeem for the greateſt part to imitate; concerning which many things ingeniouſly are, and more may be taught, the regard whereof is not to be neglected: becauſe that being repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the greateſt matters, we believe them judiciouſly inſtituted. Therefore leſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:108455:31"/> any one ſhould demand of me in theſe commentaries in what manner he ſhould bring home his choſen Wife, I ſhall ſubjoin ſome few things collected out of the ancient Annals. I determine to take my beginning from God, from whom Reaſon hath preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Learned Perſons, Neceſſity the <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> Cuſtome the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and Nature it ſelf hath in a manner inſtructed us to begin. At the firſt therefore the Ancients ſolemnized thoſe moſt holy things with a certain care, that God himſelf might more openly and evidently be a witneſs of that moſt holy Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. Where, as with us the immortal God, and at <hi>Athens Hymenaeus,</hi> ſo at <hi>Rome Thalaſſius</hi> was invocated that the Marriage might be good, happy, proſperous, and fortunate; For <hi>Thalaſſius</hi> that much eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed young Man, and one of the moſt dear fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Souldiers of <hi>Romulus,</hi> and excelling in the glory of a Warlike praiſe, was the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, love, and delight of all Men: for at the Rape of the <hi>Sabines</hi> a certain moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Virgin, although ſhe was preſerved by his Authority, was ſnatch'd away from him by his almoſt unknown Companions; but the amiable and popular commemorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Thalaſſius</hi> delivered her from that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent peril: with whom when he was hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:108455:32"/> married, the Cuſtom of invocating him was introduced in Nuptials. Therefore (that my diſcourſe may return from whence I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed) there is ſuch an efficacy, ſuch an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this Nuptial Compact, that the illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous duty to Parents is obſcured by the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of this alliance; for the husband may, as well by the Authority of the Ancients as of our Religion, ſo confine his Affections to the love of his wife, that (others being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted) he may eſteem, delight in, and pleaſe her. Hither refers that moſt grave witneſs <hi>Homer,</hi> who aſſerts, that <hi>Hector</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he could undauntedly ſuſtain the loſs of his Parents, Brethren, and laſtly of his Country, yet he could not bear the thoughts of the future dangers of <hi>Andromache</hi> his well deſerving wife. Herein <hi>Barbarus</hi> that moſt valiant Hero is ſo meek and ſo mild, that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily he may be thought to have been another perſon: For being exalted with the glory of his paſt actions, he anxiouſly, penſively, and ſadly complained, nothing concerning his own, many things concerning the event of his wife. Therefore, leſt I be tedious, we will acquieſce in this one Example; for truly the frequent (and many more than I wiſh) Examples hereof every where, which are often unworthily compacted, do aſperſe the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:108455:32"/> Authors with many ſtains of infamy. I omit now the Garlands wherewith both the Spouſe and the Poſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> were wont to be adorned. I now paſs by the Furniture and other Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, which as herein I do not diſapprove, ſo I judge them accommodated to magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence. It was a Cuſtom, that thoſe Fingers of the wife ſhould be adorned with Gold Rings, which were next to the little Fingers of the left hand, whence it is believed that they are called Ring Fingers, that it might be a perpetual monument before their Eyes of great love to their Husbands; for from thoſe Fingers (as ſome Authors affirm) ſome particular Nerves extend themſelves to the heart. It was a Cuſtom that water and fire ſhould be carried before the Bride, and that ſhe ſhould touch them both, that it might be evident that the wife was chiefly for the ſake of propagation of Iſſue: for as heat and moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture (which excel in thoſe Elements) are the cauſes of Generation; ſo the union of man and woman is chiefly introduced for the propagation of Iſſue. Brides are wont to be careful, leſt they ſhould touch their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Threſhold with their Feet, but they enter, being carried over, that they may ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie that they loſe their ſollicited Virginity, not voluntarily, but in a manner by compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:108455:33"/> wherefore among thoſe Ancients it was not lawful that Virgins ſhould be eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as well on certain days, as alſo on all the Calends dedicated to <hi>Janus,</hi> becauſe a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in a manner ſeemed to be done to them, which then was a hainous offence; yet at theſe times no Religion prohibited the Marriages of Widow; becauſe (as <hi>Verrius Flaccus</hi> aſſerts) we may on Holy-days ſcour old Ditches, but we may not make new. The ignorant Heathens have dedicated the Threſhold to <hi>Janus,</hi> who leſt in the firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs he ſhould ſeem, as it were, to be ſpurn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and neglected, it was the Cuſtom to be lifted over, not to go over the Threſhold: Alſo on Holy-days wherein the multitude of people were entertained with <hi>Lupercal,</hi> or <hi>Megalenſian,</hi> or <hi>Circenſian</hi> Sports, or with ſome other ſpectacle, the Marriages of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins were prohibited; but they were permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Widows. Some think that this was chiefly inſtituted for this reaſon, that Virgins might obſerve thoſe days, remembring that the <hi>Sabines</hi> were raviſhed upon a day of Sports; which matter attracted much diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and was the beginning of a grievous and perillous War: But it was not prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited to Widows, or to them who were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorced, for they had no cauſe to bluſh, if
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:108455:33"/> (their former Husbands being either dead or living) all the people were abſent, being at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive in the Theatre whilſt they celebrated their Nuptials.</p>
                  <p>It is expedient (if our Eſtates will permit) that our Marriages be ſplendid, neither ſhould we deprive them of this part of praiſe; for many worthy perſons have applauded Banquets, and the Sports of Gladiators, and the preparations of Paſtimes for the people; with which <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> was ſo pleaſed, that he termed the Expences of this ſort, which appertained to the entertainment of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, the moſt delightful product of riches. Why ſhould I now mention <hi>Q Mulius, C. Appius, Hortenſius Syllanus, P. Lentulus, Scaurus, Pompey,</hi> thoſe <hi>Craſſus's</hi> and <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius's,</hi> who delightfully ended the Curule Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice with the moſt magnificent Feſtivals and Solemnities? which yet have been and are reproved by many moſt grave perſons: But I can find none who diſapprove the ſplendour of Nuptials, many who approve it. <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi> that moſt learned perſon, who is wont to be ſtiled the principal and chief of the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, in thoſe Books which he hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten concerning Manners, approveth this kind of magnificence even in the beſt men. That excellent perſon and moſt famous Philoſopher,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:108455:34"/> 
                     <hi>Manuel Chryſoloras,</hi> eſpouſed to a Wife his moſt learned Nephew, and that moſt excellent Gentleman, <hi>John;</hi> for whoſe Nuptials when there was a moſt ſplendid preparation, and therefore the dignity of that grave Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher was reproached by one of his Familiars, he ſaid, O ye Gods grant better things, it is permitted us to be magnificently joyful in the moſt delightful things, and unleſs we be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to our Neighbours, that ſplendour which is ſuitable to the dignity of our Family can no where be omitted. Why ſhould we ſay more? the matter it ſelf, which always avails moſt, ſpeaks for it ſelf, and needeth not a longer diſcourſe: But large Banquets, which elſewhere are diſapproved, here they are not diſliked. Moreover we know that the Cuſtom of the <hi>Sabines</hi> was to introduce pleaſant diſcourſe, that no occaſion may be omitted of exhilarating body and mind; for the ſame reaſon Stage-Players were admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, who were ſo much eſteemed in the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> that, all the Maſters of that Art be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead, they ſent for Players out of <hi>Hetru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> that moſt flouriſhing Province of <hi>Italy;</hi> of whom he who was the eldeſt, and moſt skilful in his Art, was called <hi>Hiſtrus</hi> (as <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius Ruffus</hi> relates) from whom afterwards all the other were termed <hi>Hiſtriones,</hi> as
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:108455:34"/> the <hi>Epicureans, Pythagoreans,</hi> and <hi>Gnathons,</hi> are ſo nominated from their Authors. It is moſt certain, that Neighbours and Kindred were invited to Marriages, both in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and our Age, that all, to whom either the honour or the pleaſure of the Nuptials ſhould extend, might rejoice with them. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> (one of the ſeven Wiſe men) inſtituted, that when a Wife is joined to her Husband, ſhe ſhould eat a Quince, that he might in a manner ſignifie, that the ſweet voice and pleaſant ſpeech of the Wife ſhould be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the Husband. A Bridegroom when he enters the Bridal Bed, to complete the Marriage Rites the Brides face is hidden under a Vail, and the Bridegroom embraces her in the dark, <hi>Venus</hi> being the Bride-maid; and having laid himſelf on his Brides lap, expects a pleaſant ſleep; which we conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture to be appointed, leſt her Virgin-like modeſty ſhould more obſtinately reſiſt his lawful embraces than is meet; and leſt any ſadneſs ſhould intervene in that moſt joyful Solemnity, they had a Cuſtom to ſcatter Nuts, that the great multitude might not hear the cryes which the Bride utters either for grief or modeſty, for the Childrens ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs in gathering and cracking their Nuts. Many things reſtrain me from proceeding
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:108455:35"/> farther upon this ſubject. Firſt, leſt, if I ſhould relate theſe things more largely, I ſhould offend your ears, which, when you have applyed your mind, care, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to theſe excellent Studies of humanity, nothing but an innocent ſpeech, and a grave diſcourſe, and well compoſed things can ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie. Moreover, becauſe I think I have ſaid enough courteouſly to admoniſh our young men, wherein they may imitate thoſe Ancients whoſe Vertues are illuſtrated in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, and reſemble them as well in other things, as chiefly in this, as much as the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity of our Religion permits. Which that I may more eaſily concede to them, I have not diſcourſed of all things; but that alſot variety it ſelf may be added to the benefi hereof, out of many things I have aſſigned a few to this matter. Therefore I ceaſe not to exhort them that they pay the greateſt gratitude to thoſe Ancients, by whoſe vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance and writings (unleſs they be deficient to themſelves) they will both be advantaged themſelves, and will obtain better inſtructed Wives, and more ornate Nuptials.</p>
                  <p>Enough of theſe things, let us come to greater matters.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:108455:35"/>
            <div n="2" type="book">
               <head>DIRECTIONS FOR <hi>Love and Marriage.</hi> BOOK II.</head>
               <head type="sub">Concerning the duty of a Wife.</head>
               <p>THE next thing is that we ſhould diligently conſider that point, (viz. the Wives duty) to which long ſince our diſcourſe did tend; for this ſecond place is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for it in the firſt Book; for ſo I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed that I would firſt treat concerning the choice, afterwards concerning the duty of a Wife: this is the remaining part, this acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on remains, in which if wives, either of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:108455:36"/> their own accord, or by the precepts of their Husbands, ſhall obey me, no body will be ſo unjuſt a Judge of things, but may think that I have ſo eſtabliſhed the wives duty, that the young perſons may enjoy a ſecure tranquillitie and repoſe through the whole courſe of their lives. Therefore there are three things which being well performed by the wife make the marriage moſt lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and admirable; love to her Husband, Modeſty of Life, and a great and diligent care of the domeſtick affairs: we will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain the former, but firſt we will ſay ſome things concerning the facilitie of obedience, which ſhould be her guide and aſſiſtant, than which nothing is more acceptable, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more deſired; which thoſe moſt wiſe ancients well conſidered, by whom it was inſtituted, that when a Sacrifice was offered to <hi>Juno</hi> (who was called <hi>Gamelia</hi> from her government of marriages) the gall was taken out of the victime; that they might wiſely admoniſh, as it were by Laws, that all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and anger ſhould be excluded from the conjugal ſtate: wherefore the anſwer of a <hi>Spartan</hi> woman is approved by many learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men; for when ſhe was provoked by the ſlanderous reproaches of a certain doat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing old Woman againſt her Husband, ſhe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:108455:36"/> ſaid, Miſchief light on thee! when I was but a Child I learnt to obey my Parents, now it is chiefly neceſſary for me to obey my Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, if I will be what I ought to be; for a Husband may command, to whoſe will it is moſt fit that the Wife conform her manners. Wherefore <hi>Gorgon</hi> may deſervedly be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, who, being asked whether or no ſhe would go to her Husband, ſaid, no truly, but let him come to me. <hi>Cyrus</hi> that great Perſon and Emperour, ſaid to his Souldiers, that if their Enemies ſhould clamorouſly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault them, they ſhould ſilently ſuſtain their fury; but, on the contrary, if they were ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, that they ſhould engage with them with noiſe and ſhouting: So we inſtruct Wives, if their Husbands being angry ſhall more ſeverely chide them, than their Ears have been accuſtomed to endure, let them ſilently ſuſtain their wrath; but if grief makes them ſilent, they may ſpeak, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite, exhort, comfort, and pleaſe their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, with ſweet and affectionate diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. They who are converſant with Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants do not wear white Garments, nor they red who are with wild Oxen; for by ſuch colours thoſe Beaſts are more and more enraged. Many Authors aſſert that Tygers are diſquieted with Bells, and greatly diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:108455:37"/> therewith: So it is expedient to exhort Wives; for truly if any Garment ſhall ſeem offenſive to their Husbands, we adviſe them to abſtain from it; that they may not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agree with ſome Husbands, they muſt live mildly and pleaſingly: I think that the Ears defences (for ſo they are called, from co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the Ears) to be far more neceſſary for Wives than Wreſtlers; for theſe, their Ears only are lyable to blows, but Bills of Divorce, accompanied with grievous Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny, are obvious to the others; wherefore they muſt be very careful not to entertain ſuſpicion, jealouſie, and anger by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance of their Ears: to which matter it conduceth much, if we imitate the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of King <hi>Alexander,</hi> for he when any one was calumniated to him was wont al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to ſtop one of his Ears that he might afterwards open it to him who deſired to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelf: truly <hi>Hermione</hi> ſeemeth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the truth, who acknowledgeth, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently teſtifies, that ſhe was ruined by wicked Women, with whom ſhe was fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar: Wives therefore if at any time they fall into ſuſpicions, let them not regard ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous Women, let their Ears be ſtopped, let mutterings be exploded, neither (as the Proverb ſaith) let Fire be added to Fire:
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:108455:37"/> let them learn and diſcourſe of the expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Philip</hi> that moſt famous King, he, ſome of his Family ſometimes urging him to be more greatly angry with the <hi>Grecians,</hi> who althou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h they had received many benefits from him, yet they ſlandered and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, ſaid, What will they do then if we alſo injure them? In like manner when ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Women ſay, Your Husband little eſteems you, who are affectionate and moſt loving to him; the Wife ſhould anſwer, What if with my modeſty I ſhould forſake my chaſtity, and with my love ſhould witting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and willingly withdraw from him my great obſervance towards him?</p>
               <p>A certain Maſter found a Fugitive Servant in a Houſe of Correction, and as if he had now been puniſhed enough, he ſaid, Where had I rather find thee than in this very place? A Wife, who is grievous to her Husband by reaſon of her jealouſie, and thinks and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders of a Divorce, I would ſhe would ſo think with her ſelf; Where will a Whore, (whom I always hate) be more joyful and fortunate, than if ſhe ſhall ſee me almoſt Shipwracked, whilſt in the mean time, ſhe, Sailing with proſperous Winds, ſecurely caſts Anchor in my Marriage-Bed? <hi>Euripi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> according to his Cuſtome, ſeverely
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:108455:38"/> chideth them who at Supper were accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to uſe a Harp; for that ſound is apt to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite anger and ſadneſs, rather than to recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate them who are pleaſant: ſo I may blame thoſe Wives, who although, when a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> amity and concord, they often ſleep with their Husbands, yet anger intervening they lye aſunder, and reject conjugal embraces, by the delectableneſs and artifice whereof they might eaſily be reconciled. <hi>Juno,</hi> in <hi>Homer,</hi> to whoſe care the Nuptial ties are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſignifies the ſame; for (if I well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) when ſhe ſpoke of <hi>Thetis</hi> and <hi>Oceanus</hi> ſhe profeſſed that ſhe would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their differences and unite them by love and mutual embraces. But at <hi>Rome</hi> when any difference aroſe between Husband and Wife, they entred into the Temple of the appeaſing Goddeſs, where (the Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors being withdrawn) having diſcourſed together freely, they returned home in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord: it conduceth to domeſtick care and peace, if a Wife ſhall preſerve the love of her Husband, with ſingular diligence. When <hi>Gorgias Leontinus</hi> made an Oration, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the reconciliation of the <hi>Grecians</hi> in the Olympick Games, which were celebrated, with the concourſe of all <hi>Greece,</hi> to the moſt great and moſt worthy <hi>Jupiter, Melanthus</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:108455:38"/> ſaid, That our Oratour endeavours to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us, that we ſhould all be reconciled by a League, who yet cannot induce himſelf and his Wife and his Maid (three only) mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to agree; for his Wife was jealous, becauſe <hi>Gorgias</hi> wonderfully loved his Maid. <hi>Philip</hi> was long diſpleaſed with <hi>Olympias</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> in the mean time <hi>Demaradus Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthius</hi> returned out of <hi>Greece,</hi> whom when <hi>Philip</hi> had diligently and earneſtly asked concerning the agreement of the <hi>Grecians,</hi> he ſaid, O <hi>Philip,</hi> I eſteem it a moſt diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable thing that you ſhould manifeſtly evidence your care of the peace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of all <hi>Greece,</hi> when as yet you are not reconciled to your Wife and Son: therefore if any Woman deſire to regulate her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Servants, in the firſt place ſhe ſhould agree with her Husband, leſt ſhe be thought willing to imitate that which ſhe reproves in them: that therefore by her du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhe may take care for their mutual peace and perpetual repoſe, ſhe muſt chiefly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard this, that ſhe by no means diſagree with her Husband. But of theſe things hitherto.</p>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:108455:39"/>
                  <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Concerning Conjugal Love.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>NOW let us ſpeak of conjugal love, the great efficacy and dignity whereof (as worthy Men aſſure us) in a manner expreſſeth the Pattern of a perfect friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; wherein I ſhall paſs by many things, that I may ſpeedily diſcourſe what is chiefly to be obſerved: therefore I would have a Woman love her Husband with ſo great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, faithfulneſs and affection, that nothing of diligence, love and good will may be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and let her be ſo converſant with him, that it may be moſt certain that nothing will be good to her, nothing pleaſant, without her Husband; indeed I conceive that Love it ſelf will be the greateſt aſſiſtance to this matter; for in all things it is no better, nor no ſhorter courſe to ſeem, than to be.</p>
                  <p>How much labour, how much induſtry is neceſſary for a ſlothful Husbandman to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit, if he would ſeem skilful? How much wit, how many arts have unskilful Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, horſe-riders, and harpers need of, that they may ſeem to excel others, if they would
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:108455:39"/> be employed in thoſe things which they can leaſt do? For the moſt part many things happen whereby the eounterfeit praiſe of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>griculture, Phyſick, Horſmanſhip, and Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick vaniſheth: theſe perſons (if they will take my advice) ſhall more eaſily, more ſpeedily, and more certainly attain a ſolid and expreſs repute, than if they ſhall ſuborn proclaimers of their ambitious and feigned praiſe; and becauſe in every reſpect truth overcomes imitation, the Husbandman ſhould take care to till his Field by art and labour, the Phyſitian to heal the diſtempers of men, the Horſe-rider to manage his unruly Horſes at his pleaſure, and the Muſitian ſo to delight with his melody, that nothing may be more ſweet, nothing more pleaſant to the Ears: wherefore if Wives deſire to ſeem to love their Husbands cordially, let them love them in their hearts. Let them endeavour in the firſt place that their Husbands may clearly perceive them to be both penſive and joyful according to the various ſtate of their affairs: for both congratulation is pleaſant in proſperous, and conſolation is acceptable in adverſe affairs; whatſoever things are troubleſome to them (ſo that they be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be told to a prudent perſon) let them mutually impart, let them feign nothing,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:108455:40"/> let them diſſemble nothing, let them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal nothing; oftentimes ſorrow and trouble of mind is mitigated by Counſel and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe (which ought to be moſt pleaſant with her Husband) he in a manner participating and partaking of all the preſſures and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of all her anxieties, will extinguiſh or alleviate them; but if they ſhall be very griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and more deeply fixed, ſhe ſhould make a truce with her ſorrows even ſo long, as will be expedient for her to deſire the private ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of her Husband: finally I would that Wives ſhould ſo live with their Husbands, that in a manner they might be of one mind, and if it could be done (as <hi>Pythagoras</hi> would have it in friendſhip) that two ſhould become one. That this might more eaſily be effected, the <hi>Cretenſes</hi> (who now for many Ages have been under our Dominion) permitted their daughters to be married to none but thoſe to whom the Virgins themſelves had expreſſed ſigns of love: for they believed, that thoſe would be more beloved by their Wives, who were beloved even before the Nuptial Union; for they affirm that it is appointed by Nature and approved by Cuſtom, that all actions (beſides a very few) are done in a courſe of time; for neither when we touch the fire are we preſently burned, nor doth wood thrown
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:108455:40"/> into the fire inſtantly flame; wherefore they think it neceſſary for them, that (as in the loving of Friends, ſo alſo) in Husbands they ſhould judiciouſly chuſe the reſemblance of their own minds; for they believe that they can neither be rightly known, nor ardently loved on a ſudden. Let them conſider how much this Cuſtom ſhould be approved. But truly it will not be denyed to be accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated to the concord and conſtancy of love. Neither may I paſs by thoſe in ſilence, who by amorous Potions and love Inchantments extort their Husbands love, whom I am wont to compare to Fiſhers, who render the Fiſhes taken by poyſon (as they uſe to do in ſome places of <hi>Hetruria)</hi> inſipid and almoſt uſeleſs: Alſo they ſeem like Travellers who had rather lead the blind, than follow them who ſee: Therefore mutual love ſhould be diligently and voluntarily acquired, preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and augmented.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things are illuſtrated by the lives and moſt noble actions of Women; in the imitation whereof <hi>Panthia</hi> making tryal of her ſelf, and the conſtancy of her vertue and love, wonderfully loved and delighted in her Husband <hi>Abradatus</hi> Prince of <hi>Suſa,</hi> and being a Captive preſerved her Faith to him, and made <hi>Cyrus</hi> his Friend, and did not rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſly
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:108455:41"/> waſted, but employed all her riches, all her treaſures in adorning him; he fighting moſt valiantly againſt the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociates of <hi>Croeſus,</hi> both that he might be grateful to <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and might ſeem a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band worthy of <hi>Panthia</hi> his Wife, he gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly dyed, having performed the duty of a valiant Commander and ſtout Souldier; whoſe Obſequies that ſhe might moſt nobly celebrate, ſhe ſlew her ſelf upon his dead body, ſought with ſingular diligence. <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandane</hi> ſo loved <hi>Cyrus,</hi> that when ſhe dyed it was more grievous to her to depart from <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> than from her life; wherefore <hi>Cyrus,</hi> leſt he ſhould be an ungrateful Husband, lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her a long time after her death, and for her honours ſake, commanded all thoſe whom he governed to mourn. <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> his Wife loved him ſo well, that ſhe was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to think of nothing but the affection and love of her Husband; whereby it came to paſs, that that moſt famous Governour of <hi>Grecia</hi> might yield to her in all things, and it may be truly ſaid, that ſhe could do more than the other <hi>Grecians</hi> of her time; for whatſoever ſhe deſired, the ſame <hi>Themiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> did deſire; whatſoever <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> that the <hi>Athenians</hi> wiſhed; whatſoever the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> that all <hi>Grecia</hi> deſired. <hi>Theſta,</hi> the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:108455:41"/> of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the elder, was married to <hi>Polyxenus;</hi> he afterwards being offended by the Tyrant fled for fear out of <hi>Sicily; Dionyſius</hi> calls for his Siſter, and blames her becauſe ſhe knowing of her Husbands flight, did not acquaint him therewith; <hi>Theſta,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying upon her conſtancy and ſingular vertue, anſwered, O <hi>Dionyſius</hi> do you think me ſuch a vile and baſe Woman, that if I had known of my Husbands flight, I would have refuſed to have been a Companion and partaker of his Fortune? it would truly have been more acceptable to me to be called <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyxenus</hi> his Wife, though baniſhed, than the Siſter of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Tyrant. The <hi>Syracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> admiring her noble mind, after the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants were expelled, dignified her with Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Honours; and when ſhe was dead, all ranks, all ſorts of people, and finally all the <hi>Syracuſians</hi> were preſent at her Funeral Solemnities. <hi>Armenia</hi> the Wife of <hi>Tigra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> is a noble Example to Women, for truly in that Expedition which <hi>Cyrus</hi> made againſt the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> being by no means able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the abſence of her Husband, ſhe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with a moſt willing mind every where, as an unwearied Companion through ſo great perils. <hi>Andromache,</hi> in <hi>Homer,</hi> how much ſhe is delighted with her <hi>Hector,</hi> upon
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:108455:42"/> whom ſhe placed all her love, ſhe even de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares by this expreſſion; You are my only Father, reverend Mother, and ſweet Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Husband, in all reſpects amiable: At length being diſtracted by reaſon of his death, ſhe wildly runs through the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and views the Walls. <hi>Cania,</hi> an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Woman, hath obtained a commemorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her Virtue in this place (for although the narration thereof will be long, yet the dignity, novelty, and variety, will be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, both to you, and to thoſe who ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſe theſe things) whoſe remarkable Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize we will begin to relate more copiouſly. <hi>Sinatus</hi> and <hi>Sinorix</hi> united in Kindred to each other undoubtedly excelled the other Tetrarchs of <hi>France</hi> in puiſſance, renown, and glory: of whom <hi>Sinatus</hi> eſpouſed <hi>Cania,</hi> who not only excelled in beauty of Body, but alſo in ſingular Virtue; ſhe, being indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with chaſtity, goodneſs, prudence, and magnanimity, obliged the hearts of all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to her ſelf with a certain admirable love: The Prieſthood of <hi>Diana</hi> (whom the <hi>French</hi> eſpecially worſhip) rendred her more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, in which both for the ſake of her own and her Anceſtors dignity, ſhe had the chief Authority; for at the Sacrifices being always exceedingly adorned ſhe attracted
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:108455:42"/> the Eyes of all upon her ſelf: Firſt <hi>Sinorix</hi> began to love her fervently, afterwards he intends the death of his Kinſman, becauſe he feared that whilſt the other was ſafe, his deſires could not be effected, therefore that wicked Man, blinded with the great love of his Miſtriſs, privately ſlayeth the negligent <hi>Sinatus:</hi> Not long after he earneſtly deſires to Marry <hi>Cania,</hi> who, couragiouſly ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the misfortune of her Husband, vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently endeavoured, and prudently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected an occaſion and opportunity to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge the wicked Fact of <hi>Sinorix. Sinorix</hi> urgeth that the Marriage (indeed deadly) may be accompliſhed; he alledgeth honeſt cauſes of his miſtake (if we may think that honeſt which is contaminated with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt wickedneſs) at the firſt <hi>Cania</hi> rejects his entreaties, afterwards her Relations, (that they might for ever oblige that moſt potent Prince to themſelves) earneſtly urge her to be content to Marry him; then, as if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, ſhe promiſeth that ſhe would, and henceforth ſhe entertains familiarly the young Man that was brought to her, and they entred together the Temple of <hi>Diana,</hi> that (that <hi>French</hi> Goddeſs being witneſs) their Covenant and Promiſe might be eſtabliſhed: afterwards deliberately taking a Cup in her
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:108455:43"/> Hands ſhe firſt drinks, the remainder ſhe gave to <hi>Sinorix</hi> to drink; but there was in the Cup Metheglin mixed with Poiſon, which when ſhe perceived <hi>Sinorix</hi> had drunk ſhe manifeſted her joy by her Eyes, Countenace, and Fore-head, and turning to the Image of <hi>Diana,</hi> ſhe ſpoke after this manner, O Divine Parent, I call you to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that I would not have ſurvived <hi>Sinatus</hi> (in good truth) for the love of life (which being retained indeed afflicted me with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, but being laid down may deliver me from troubles) but that I determined to live to atchieve the tranſactions of this day; nor that I ſhould have perceived any plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in my life after the Funeral of my Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, which was mournful to me, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable to his Country, unleſs a certain hope of revenge had now and then comforted me; which being now effected, I now wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly deſcend to my deareſt and beſt Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band <hi>Sinatus;</hi> O moſt cruel <hi>Sinorix,</hi> inſtead of Marriage Beds and Nuptials, Sepulchres may be prepared for you: a little while af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when as now the Poiſon had largely ſpread it ſelf through their Bodies, <hi>Sinorix</hi> firſt, then <hi>Cania</hi> died. <hi>Stratonica</hi> ſo loved her Husband <hi>Dejotarus</hi> that ſhe thought that nothing appertained to her, but how ſhe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:108455:43"/> ſhould fulfill his will and therefore ſhe great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grieved (or rather lamented) to ſee <hi>Dejo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarus</hi> afflicted, becauſe he perceived that he neither had iſſue by her, nor that ſhe could ſucceed him in the Kingdom; ſhe therefore of her own accord provides a woman comely in countenance and manners (called <hi>Electra)</hi> and perſwades, deſires, and urges her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band (who admired the affection and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of his Wife) to a privacy with her: Afterwards ſhe took care of, educated, and moſt honourably governed the Children be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of her, even as her own. I ſhould be too tedious if I ſhould repeat the earneſt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Tertia Emilia</hi> to <hi>P. Cornelius Scipio,</hi> or if I ſhould remember the exceeding great love of <hi>Julia Porcia, Artemiſia, Hipſicratea,</hi> and the other Examples of lawful love, which are obvious to all who are converſant in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory. There are alſo many things which might be given in precept, concerning the love of Wives, which we purpoſely omit; for we wholly confide to their ingenuity, both that of their own accord they will find out how they ſhould eſteem, and alſo diligently and exactly love their Husbands. Yet thoſe things which they ſhall diſcover, we hope will be little different from thoſe Precepts whereof we have diſcourſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:108455:44"/>
                  <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Concerning the moderation of a Wife.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe remaining part is concerning Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, from which moſt often a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual love between Man and Wife is begun, kept, and preſerved. This ornament is not only moſt pleaſing to Husbands, but alſo it ſeems moſt noble to all who hear thereof. Moderation in a Wife is believed chiefly to conſiſt in her countenance, behaviour, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, food, and embraces, of which we will briefly treat, if we any way underſtand them either by our own invention or learning or experience, and we will ſpeak of the two former things together, which are almoſt of the ſame nature. Above all things the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance is the moſt certain Image of the mind, which is in no living creature but in man, that he may eſteem thoſe indications of an honeſt, comely, and abſtemious mind: for in it the manners which nature hath other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe wholly hidden are eaſily diſcovered. It truly declares and ſhews many other
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:108455:44"/> things without Speech: for by the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and manner of walking, the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the mind may be known. Alſo in mute creatures we perceive Anger, Joy, and ſuch ſort of paſſions as well by other ſigns of the Body, as by their Eyes, which by their motion teſtifie and clearly manifeſt how their minds are affected; whence chiefly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny depending upon the lineaments of the face have given precepts to diſcover the nature of every one: but I too much digreſs. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I would have Wives clearly evidence their modeſty in all places and at all times. They may perform this by obſerving an equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and gravity in their Eyes in their Walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and finally in the motion of their whole Body: for the wandring of the Eyes, haſty manner of going, and the overmuch motion of the hands, and of all the other parts of the body, cannot be done without diſgrace, and are always joined with vanity and a great ſignification of levity. Wherefore they ſhould be careful that their forehead, countenance, and geſture (whereby we pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate with a judicious obſervation into the moſt ſecret affections) be applyed to the obſervance of decency: for by their diligence herein they may acquire delight and honour, but by negligence they cannot avoid diſquiets
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:108455:45"/> and cenſures. Yet I would by no means have her face to be unpleaſant, becauſe neither her aſpect ſhould ſeem rough but mild, neither ſhould the motion of her body ſeem light but pleaſantly grave. I earneſtly give this in precept, that ſhe forbear immoderate laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which being undecent in all perſons is certainly moſt hateful in a Woman: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though when there happens facetious Jeſts they are not to be blamed, if they do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what deviate from a ſerious geſture by a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt laughter. <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> was wont to compoſe his deportment at home in a Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Glaſs, that by his Eyes he might judge what he ſhould do and what he ſhould avoid in the earneſtneſs of his Oratory. We may well apply this to the concern of a Wife. I wiſh they would daily conſider and think what the dignity and gravity of a Wife re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, leſt they ſhould be deficient in a come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deportment. We know that the <hi>Spartan</hi> Wives were wont to go with their Faces co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; but the Virgins with their Faces un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered; whereof <hi>Carillus</hi> the <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> being asked, he anſwered, Our Anceſtors permitted this liberty to young Virgins that they might get Husbands, but prohibited it to married Women, that they might under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that it belonged not to them to ſeek
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:108455:45"/> Husbands, but to preſerve and keep thoſe which they had. Which Cuſtom indeed our <hi>Cretenſes</hi> allow, who permit their young Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to ſtand at their doors and ſing; and by many other ways to jeſt and play with their Woers. But they who are married (as they who are dedicated to the holy ſervices of <hi>Veſta)</hi> ſhould ſtay at home, they ſhould ſcarce ever go abroad, ſo that in a manner it may ſeem unlawful for them to behold other men. Who will not affirm, that they might extract ſuch a Cuſtom from <hi>Xenophon?</hi> Who how much he would have the Womens aſpects to be reſtrained, is evidently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived: For when <hi>Tigranes</hi> returned home together with his Parents and his moſt loving Wife <hi>Armenia,</hi> from <hi>Cyrus,</hi> others applaud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as well his ſhape as manners, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude of body, and beauty, <hi>Tigranes</hi> ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Armenia</hi> what ſhe thought of the beauty of <hi>Cyrus;</hi> but <hi>Armenia</hi> calling the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Gods to witneſs, ſaid, I never withdrew my eyes from you, therefore what the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or ſhape of <hi>Cyrus</hi> is, I am altogether igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. That of <hi>Gorgias</hi> concords hereto, who would have them ſhut up at home, ſo that nothing might be known of them beſide re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. But <hi>Thucydides</hi> thought not this fit to be allowed of; for he declares her to be the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:108455:46"/> beſt Wife of whoſe praiſe or diſpraiſe the leaſt report is diſperied. But we who follow a mediocrity do eſtabliſh more free Laws for them: For they are not to be confined in their Bed-chambers, as in Priſons; but they ſhould ſo go abroad, that this liberty which we allow them may be an evidence of their Vertue and Chaſtity: Yet Wives ſhould far otherwiſe comport themſelves to their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, than the Moon to the Sun, for when it is nigh to the Sun it is never diſcerned, but being at a diſtance from it, appears every where reſplendent; therefore I would have them to be ſeen in the preſence of their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, but in their abſence they ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir'd at home. Wherefore they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an honeſt decency in their eyes (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we have a moſt lively perception even in a Picture, which is called a tacite Poetry) and in the motion of the head, and in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther demeanours of their bodies. I have diſcourſed concerning the countenance and geſture, now I ſhall treat concerning their ſpeech.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:108455:46"/>
                  <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Concerning the ſpeech and ſilence of Women.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I <hi>Socrates</hi> exhorteth men to ſpeak either thoſe things which they certainly know, or which, with their honour, they cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal: We enjoin women to concede the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer as proper to men, but they may believe the latter alſo common to themſelves; in whom loquacity cannot be enough reproved, by the moſt prudent and learned perſons, nor taciturnity ſufficiently applauded. Whence by the excellent Inſtitutes of the <hi>Romans</hi> it was prohibited them to plead publick or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Cauſes; from which when both <hi>Amaſia,</hi> and <hi>Affrania,</hi> and <hi>Hortenſia,</hi> deviated, it was reproved, blamed, and rebuked in their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals. <hi>Marcus Cato</hi> the elder when he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the <hi>Roman</hi> women, contrary to the order of Nature, and the modeſty of the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Sex, ſometimes to be converſant in the Courts of Judicature, and ambitiouſly to purſue honour, and to diſcourſe with Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, he inveighed againſt, reproved, and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:108455:47"/> reſtrained them, as the honour of that moſt grave Citizen and of that Empire required. We know that the <hi>Pythagoreans</hi> were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be ſilent for no leſs a time than two years at their firſt entrance, leſt (which is a ſhameful thing) they ſhould ſeem to be circumvented, deceived, and to erre, or leſt that they ſhould obſtinately defend that which as yet they had not perfectly compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended: But we appoint to Wives a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual time and ſpace of ſilence, whereſoever any acceſs to levity, diſhoneſty, and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſhall appear; being ſpoken to, they ſhould anſwer moſt modeſtly to their familiar Friends, and make them civil ſalutations, and they ſhould ſo briefly diſpatch thoſe things which place and occaſion ſhall offer, that they may rather be thought to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked to, than to provoke diſcourſe; they ſhould alſo endeavour to be rather praiſed for a diſcreet brevity, than an eloquent prolixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſpeech. <hi>Theano,</hi> when ſhe put forth her hand to take her Mantle, a certain young man turning to his Companions, ſaid, How handſom is that Arm! to whom ſhe anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, It is not a common one. Wherefore it is expedient, that not only the arms, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the diſcourſes of a woman ſhould not be common; for the ſpeech of ſuch a woman
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:108455:47"/> is not leſs to be feared, than the nakedneſs of the body; truly they muſt avoid the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe of Strangers, whereby they are wont to diſcover their manners and affections with great facility; ſilence alſo is often commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the moſt excellent perſons. <hi>Pindarus</hi> highly extols that moſt excellent Prince of <hi>Greece, Epaminondas,</hi> becauſe knowing much he ſaid little; for he herein (as in many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things) obſerved the excellent dictates of Nature, who, being the director of life, evidently demonſtrates her thoughts o ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; for ſhe hath prudently beſtowed on us two Ears, and but one Tongue, guarded indeed with the double defence of Lips and Teeth; for this is chiefly granted to us (as <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> and many learned men ſay) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that property placed in us produceth the beſt and moſt pleaſant fruits, whereas Foundations of Knowledge often, moſt often of ignorance are laid through the other ſenſes Nature hath granted to us, as Agents<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers: yet a certain Citizen of ours (whom for the preſent I need not name to you) commends ſilence only in thoſe, by whom neither ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe can be obtained by wit, nor authority by prudence, nor repute by their ornate ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; whom I am wont to anſwer, that the chiefeſt conſiderations in every reſpect are to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:108455:48"/> be referred as well to the perſons and places as to the times; for if I ſhould grant, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Opinion, that it were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times expedient for men, yet I ſhould judge it, for the moſt part, repugnant to the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, gravity and ſtability of a Wife: wherefore <hi>Sophocles</hi> (in my Opinion truly not worſe than this Citizen of whom I now ſpeak, all men affirm him to be better) hath termed ſilence a ſingular ornament in Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: therefore they ſhould think that they ſhall obtain the glory of Eloquence, if they adorn themſelves with the famous ornament of ſilence; for neither the praiſe of a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matory Play, nor the applauſe and flattery of an Oration, but an eloquent, and well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved, and grave ſilence is required of them. But what do I do? I muſt take heed, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſince I treat of ſilence, leſt perchance I ſeem to thee too talkative.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Concerning the Apparel and Attire of a Wife.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT remains that we diſcourſe concerning the apparel, and the other attire of the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:108455:48"/> Body, the proportion whereof being neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not only the Matrimony, but oftentimes the Patrimony is deſtroyed; all evidence this to me, who are careful in conſidering theſe things: but if the never enough praiſed mediocrity ſhall delight them, and if they ſhall approve themſelves to be modeſt, they will both provide for their domeſtick wealth, and otherwiſe in a manner, inſtruct the whole City: in this place that worthy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſhould be moſt eſteemed, that they ſhould be careful in this matter of ſplendour, rather to ſhun ignominy, than to acquire ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe; for thoſe who are nobly born (if their eſtates permit) ſhould not wear mean and deſpicable garments: truly we judge that this is chiefly to be referred to the regard of the Eſtate, and Place, and Perſon, and Time. Who can without-laughter behold a Pope cloathed in a Souldiers habit, or one wearing a Senators Garment in a School, or one in a Gown at a Horſe race? But yet neither one who is too curious, nor one who is very negligent ſhall be approved, but they who ſhall obſerve a decency in their Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits; for firſt an over great indulgence here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in argueth much vanity; moreover it is wont to evidence and to occaſion a deviation from their Husbands to other Lovers. King <hi>Cyrus</hi>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:108455:49"/> may be an Example to our Women, that they ſhould not with ſo much earneſtneſs ſeek coſtly Attire for themſelves, who truly ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as well for his admirable wiſdom, as for the ſplendour of his moderation, correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to his noble Name; for in the <hi>Perſian</hi> Language the Sun is called <hi>Cyrus:</hi> To whoſe Uncle <hi>Cyaxares</hi> Ambaſſadors came from an <hi>Indian</hi> King to treat of Peace with the <hi>Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> to whom that he might ſhew himſelf with the choiceſt of his Army, he ſent order to his General <hi>Cyrus</hi> to appear very ſpeedily with all his Troops in the Royal Palace-yard, and the moſt large Market-place; he obeyed the Command, and having put on a ſlight Garment, he came both with diſcipline and valour, and admirable celerity, although <hi>Cyaxares</hi> had ſent him a Purple Robe and a precious Chain, and other Ornaments, that that Nephew and General of the King might be more adorned and ſplendid; but <hi>Cyrus</hi> magnanimouſly contemned all theſe things, and ſeemed ſufficiently adorned both to himſelf and others, when like a warlike per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he was perceived to arrive with his well diſciplin'd Army almoſt as ſoon as the Royal Purſuivant was returned to <hi>Cyaxares:</hi> So a diſeſteem of ſuch Apparel will be a great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to Wives. <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Tyrant of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:108455:49"/> 
                     <hi>Sicily</hi> gave two moſt precious Garments to <hi>Lyſander,</hi> that his Daughters might be more adorned; they having refuſed them, <hi>Lyſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> commanded them to be returned to <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius,</hi> ſaying, that his Daughters would be more ornate without them. <hi>Julia</hi> the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> imagining that her gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous Attire was ſometimes offenſive to her Father, the next day having put on ordinary Habit, ſhe came to ſee and to pay her duty to her Father; which when <hi>Caeſar</hi> greatly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, ſhe then acknowledged that ſhe then indeed ſought Attire pleaſing to the Eyes of her Father, but before of her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band <hi>Agrippa.</hi> Every one may think as he will, yet I believe that others are chiefly eſteemed, and that all thoſe vain Ornaments are delighted in, rather that they may, by ſo great care and vigilance, pleaſe others, than their Husbands; for theſe things are diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded at home, but abroad this Ruiner of our Eſtates cannot be ſufficiently decked nor adorned. Truly variety of precious Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is ſeldom uſeful, but often grievous to Husbands; yet they are always pleaſing to Lovers, for whoſe ſake theſe things are invented. I am wont to compare thoſe who allow theſe ſuperfluous Ornaments to their Wives, to them, who appear ſo ſplendid,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:108455:50"/> and have ſuch pleaſant Houſes, that although they omit neceſſary expences within their Houſes, yet their exterior form will ſeem glorious, and their Houſes delectable to their Neighbours and to Paſſengers; they are alſo like to unskilful, but rich, Barbers to whom young men never go but to be trimm'd; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are their Ivory and curiouſly poliſhed Looking-Glaſſes advantageous, but rather troubleſome to them, when they may daily ſee and behold, to their great grief, moſt noble young men in their neighbouring Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers Shops: Alſo this moſt ſumptuous Attire, this moſt magnificent ſplendour, this moſt luxurious Apparel maketh it moſt pleaſant to them to frequent Porches, Entries, and Walks, and very often to ramble through the whole City: Wherefore moſt wiſely it was prohibited the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Women to wear fine Shoes, that they might be reſtrained from wandring. Truly if we take away from moſt Women their precious Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they will voluntarily and willingly ſtay at home: Yet I think this Cuſtom (for as much as it is ſo much degenerated) ſhould be imitated, to adorn them (if our Eſtates will permit) with Gold, Jewels, and Pearls; for ſuch ſigns rather of a rich, than luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Woman, rather evidence the magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:108455:50"/> of the Husband, than enſnare wanton Eyes. I omit that this ſort of riches is more durable, and portends leſs danger of indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, than the other; they may often alſo, with greater facility, be great aſſiſtants to both private and publick Affairs: Who is ignorant how advantageous this ſort of mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence was in time paſt to the <hi>Romans?</hi> out of which, in the moſt grievous <hi>Punick</hi> War, the City raiſed money, (which the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients termed the ſinews of War) by the Appian Law: yet I Judge that it is fit for them not to allow themſelves ſo great a liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in theſe things as thoſe Laws permitted. Wherefore I would have them to abſtain from a too licentious Apparel and other At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire of the body, that it may be thought that they are not reſtrained from it by neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, but deſerve the reward of praiſe for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing what they might have had. This ſhall ſuffice concerning Apparel.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Concerning the Food of a Wife.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>NOW we ſhall diſcourſe concerning Food, wherein all who conſider theſe
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:108455:51"/> things do accord with me that there is the greateſt efficacy in every reſpect. Who doubts that the ſtrength of Vertue is truly enervated and deſtroyed by thoſe Luxuries, wherein the multitude believe they may live delightfully? What ſeverity is ſo great which in a ſhort time cannot be corrupted? Who is ſo involved in enſuality that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not by ſobriety, care, and vigilance, acquire the pleaſure and praiſe of a moderate life? That therefore Wives may be deficient in no part of modeſty, I would have them to be careful chiefly to abſtain from theſe things whereby ſenſuality is wont to be generated, eſtabliſhed, and increaſed: The holy Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins were inſtructed by the beſt and moſt prudent perſons to watchings, and to abſtain from meat and drink, leſt luxury ſhould ſtain their pure thoughts, and debilitate their firm minds. In time paſt the uſe of Wine was unknown to the <hi>Roman</hi> Women, and now alſo is prohibited to the <hi>Syrians</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians;</hi> which that it might more eaſily be diſcovered by obſervation, a Kiſs was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed at <hi>Rome</hi> amongſt Kindred, that the ſmell might be an argument againſt thoſe who were intemperate; but thoſe Women who tranſgreſſed the Law, not only were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly accounted infamous, but (as <hi>Cato</hi>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:108455:51"/> aſſerts) it was the Law that they ſhould be grievouſly fined; for this kind of intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance very often allures and induces to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful pleaſures: Whence wiſely ſome Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens placed together the Images of <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> in the ſame Temple, that they who came with an earneſt deſire to ſee the Image of <hi>Venus,</hi> might firſt honour the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of <hi>Bacchus;</hi> truly the minds and ſpirits of ſuch perſons being become impotent can think of nothing that is difficult, remember nothing honourable, nor underſtand any thing divine, but being void of judgment and reaſon, they through a certain inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Senſes conceive that to be their chiefeſt good, which (as <hi>Cicero</hi> writes) if brutes could ſpeak they would call ſenſuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Cyrus</hi> eaſily overthrew the preparations of <hi>Spargapiſes</hi> the Son of <hi>Tomyres</hi> with his moſt excellent Army, extinguiſhed his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, and repreſſed his boldneſs, when he, being valiant and prepared, chaſed, enſnared, and put to flight <hi>Spargapiſes</hi> (weakned with riotous Banquettings and Wine) from his Enterpriſe. Did not the effeminacies of <hi>Capua</hi> more debilitate the ſtrength of <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibal,</hi> than the ſlaughter of <hi>Canna</hi> conſumed the <hi>Romans?</hi> What need we Examples? Unleſs a moſt moderate care of their Food
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:108455:52"/> ſhall be their conduct, the ſhipwracked mind having forſaken the limits of tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, will be precipitated into ruine. Of ſo many kinds and natural inclinations of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, there is ſcarce any, who if he was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cately educated in a voluptuous obſcurity, could attain to even ſo much as a counterfeit moderation, or the appearance of a decent deportment. They who follow the guidance of Nature are content with a little; but they who purſue delights with a certain ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſatiety, always deſire that which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe and infinite. I am pleaſed with the frugality of that <hi>Lacon,</hi> who having got lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Fiſhes, gave them to the Cook to be dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; the Cook according to his Cuſtom de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires Cheeſe, Oyl, Vinegar, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, that they might be ſeaſoned more deliciouſly; to whom <hi>Lacon</hi> ſaid, if I had thoſe things which you demand, I ſhould have no need of the little Fiſhes. Filthy luſt and unchaſte embraces not only attend upon, but alſo eagerly purſue <hi>Alexandrian</hi> delights, and <hi>Syracuſian</hi> Feaſts. Moſt excellently the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> that they might manifeſt to their Wives and Children the deformity of intemperate drinking, exhibited drunken Servants at their Banquets, where when ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Cuſtom, they had, by their
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:108455:52"/> follies, attracted the Eyes of all the Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors upon themſelves, they not only ſeemed worthy of pity, but alſo they ſeemed miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and unhappy; neither do I believe that thoſe famous perſons were delighted with the miſeries of thoſe Servants, but they judged whatſoever was filthy in them would be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable in Freemen: So Wives ſhould exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerve drunken Maid-ſervants, that they may conſider what they ſhould chiefly avoid; for although (as <hi>Homer</hi> ſaith) Wine unto wearied bodies a great vigour gives; yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken immoderately, it both renders the Mind feeble, and leaves the Senſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed to old age; for the excellency of its ardour cauſeth that that heat which Nature hath beſtowed on us being vanquiſhed by a more violent force is not maturely but ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly conſumed. How much alſo that dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and unruly vapour impedes the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of affairs, is evident, for truly as their opinions are not rational, ſo they can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther argue, nor refute, nor well diſcourſe. Why ſhould I ſay more? The Poets report, that very many, by this matter chiefly, have of Men become Swine, Aſſes, and Lions; which that it may be avoided, they muſt be ſo much more diligently careful, becauſe both by the ſtupidity of their wit, and vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:108455:53"/> from weighty Affairs (as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denceth to us) they are more propenſe to theſe kinds of Vices; alſo the diſpoſition of the Mother, and the moderation of her life, will be an aid to the Children, to whom all theſe things for the greateſt part are decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Therefore <hi>Diogenes,</hi> very aptly, when he beheld a drunken Boy, ſaid, Drunken Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents begat you. How much the education of a temperate Mother may avail them when born, we will a little after diſcourſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ought to admoniſh and exhort our Wives to follow the inſtinct of Nature, and to diſeſteem and reject ſenſual pleaſures (within whoſe Dominion Vertue can by no means conſiſt) and rather to approve and imitate the frugal Tables of <hi>Lucretia,</hi> than the ſumptuous delicacies of the <hi>Tarquins,</hi> and of <hi>Cleopatra;</hi> whereby they will provide for both their own honour, and for their Children, to whom they owe all things. Now in its place we will briefly treat concerning Congreſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:108455:53"/>
                  <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Concerning the regulation of Congreſs.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SO truly the matter is, that what rules of meat and drink, ſuch a proportion of congreſs ſhould in a manner be obſerved: for truly congreſs it ſelf followeth the rules of life) as a young Chicken her dam; and this may be unodrſtood by many reaſons and examples: we cannot, in this place, begin more wiſely and more aptly to the purpoſe of our diſcourſe than from nature it ſelf, that we may briefly declare whatſoever we think. Firſt indeed, becauſe the union of Man and Wife (as we have above ſaid) was chiefly ordain'd and ought to be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the ſake of Children, they muſt uſe conjugal embraces chiefly with the hope of propagating Iſſue; we ſufficiently under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and perceive what manner of nature there is in moſt Beaſts, which for this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hath appointed them certain Laws of Congreſs, that the mortal kinds of living creatures might in a manner be rendered im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:108455:54"/> by a perpetual ſucceſſion; wherein they may be examples to us (to whom a more free and noble deſire is given) that we ſhould not mutually embrace for the ſake of pleaſure, but of generating Iſſue; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we admoniſh (that I may uſe the words of <hi>Julia</hi> the daughter of <hi>Auguſtus)</hi> that when a Ship is full, they admit no other paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; neither therefore ſhould they think Beaſts are chiefly upon that account Beaſts, becauſe never when great with young, but always for the ſake of generation, they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite their Venereal Appetites; but if Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhall paſs theſe limits, even at leaſt let them govern themſelves ſo that they may be, and be accounted, modeſt in this part of moderation, from which modeſty is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated, to which matter we think it may chiefly conduce, if, at the firſt, Husbands ſhall accuſtom them to ſeem to be helpers, not of luſt, but of neceſſity: but they ſhould ſo evidence their Nuptial Honour and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, that in their congreſs decency may accompany their embraces, leſt by their avidity, and immodeſty, they be both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective in their Honour, and alſo leſs accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to their tacite Husbands. <hi>Herodotus</hi> writes that Women lay aſide their Modeſty together with their inner garments; if they
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:108455:54"/> embrace adulterers, we plainly confeſs it, but if their Husbands, they will always ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a decency. When a certain Woman was drawn by force from the preſence of <hi>Philip</hi> becauſe of her luſt and fury, ſhe ſaid, every Woman, if thou takeſt away the light, is like and the ſame with others; this may truly be ſaid to adulterers; but wives, although the light be far removed, ſhould not make themſelves like to vile Women. What is it which <hi>Heſiod</hi> forbids to be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely diſcloſed in the night? becauſe (as he ſaith) the nights belong to the immortal Gods; for a Wife ought at no time to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in her duty, and although her body cannot be beheld, yet ſhe ſhould preſerve a modeſty in all places, that ſhe may deſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeem well behaved to her Husband even in the dark: Wherefore very excellently <hi>Commodus Caeſar,</hi> when his Wife endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to perſwade him to uſe unuſual and diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed pleaſures with her, anſwered, How much it is fit to obey other Women in theſe things, let them look to it, a Wife certainly is a Name of honour, not of pleaſure. Wherefore <hi>Cato</hi> the Cenſor ejected <hi>Manilius</hi> out of the Senate, becauſe he kiſſed his Wife in the preſence of his Daughter: If ſo be that it is moſt undecent to kiſs a Wife or
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:108455:55"/> amorouſly embrac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> her in the preſence of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n, how much more expedient is it, that nothing immoderate, nothing wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, ſhould be offered before the Eyes of Husbands, whom Wives ought chiefly to pleaſe? <hi>Hieron</hi> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ned <hi>Epicharmus,</hi> the Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian, a great ſum of Money, becauſe he publickly declared a certain undecent thing in the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſence of his Wife; for the dignity of Wedlock is ſo venerable, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is fit no acceſs ſhould be apparent to the Eyes and Ears of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rangers. The moderation of the <hi>Athenians</hi> demonſtrated this excellent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when they reſtored the intercepted Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Philip,</hi> which he had wrote to <hi>Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias,</hi> inviolate; for indeed they judged it unfit for Strangers, or truly Enemies, to partake of the ſecrets of a Wife: It is meet therefore that they always be eareful and mindful concerning this matter, hereby they may acquire praiſe, triumphs, and a Crown of Gold; nothing ſhould be ſo pleaſant or delightful to them, as ever to avert them from the duty of a modeſt mind: Wherein ſince they may imitate many moſt illuſtrious women, I know not whether <hi>Braſilla</hi> be moſt excellent, whoſe noble enterprize ought not to be omitted in this Age; for ſhe (being born of Noble Parents of <hi>Dyrrachium,</hi> as it is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:108455:55"/> by approved Authors) being taken in an Excurſion of Enemies, was in danger of being raviſhed; this woman truly, in that great peril, purely and entirely preſerved her chaſtity by her moſt beautiful aſpect, wit, vertue, and magnanimity; for by many words ſhe appeaſed the violence, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained the fury of <hi>Cericus</hi> the Conquerour; ſhe undertook if he would defend her cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity (inſtead of a Ranſom) by a certain Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick Oyntment to make him invulnerable by all military Arms; this diſcourſe of this noble and modeſt woman, and his great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of Magick obtained his belief, and he anxiouſly expected the event of the matter, having placed Guards upon her whilſt the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Maid gathered ſome Roots; then ſhe magnanimouſly came to the Warriour, and promiſeth that ſhe would make tryal not by words, but by Herbs; moreover when ſhe had annointed his neck with the Juice, ſhe ſheweth him his throat, but <hi>Cericus,</hi> as if he would be ſafely raſh, cuts off his head with his Sword, and admired that teſtimony of her moſt chaſte mind. Why ſhould I recite more? They will neither want Examples nor Exhortations, if they would be ſuch as they ought to be. And leſt we ſhould any longer defer thoſe things which are moſt
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:108455:56"/> diligently to be conſidered by us, we put a period to theſe things.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Concerning Domeſtick care.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BOth the time and the place require our diſcourſe concerning Domeſtick care; concerning which I would have thoſe few things expected, which we perceive, by common experience, moſt expedient; but thoſe things which are written by learned men I cannot include within this little and narrow place, becauſe neither do all things appertain to this diſcourſe and time, and every one may know thoſe things by their Books; it ſhall ſuffice out of many things, that thoſe things which are neceſſary, and may be treated of very briefly and moſt ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily, ſhall not be pretermitted in theſe our little Commentaries. I would have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the whole care of the Domeſtick Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs chiefly employed about Eſtates, and Servants (or dependents) and the education of Children; we will briefly treat of this laſt, but we will firſt diſpatch thoſe two former points; for we eſteem the care of our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:108455:56"/> and diligence about our Servants, and dependents neceſſary; for we have need of eſtates and ſervants, without the plenty and aſſiſtance whereof the family affairs cannot conſiſt; in which things truly the moderation of domeſtick affairs is for the moſt part con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd: and which unleſs they be eſtabliſhed by the Councils and Precepts of the Wife have no Foundation and are wont to be in great diſorder: for as naturally men are endued with a ſtrength of Body and Mind, as well for other cauſes, as that they may enrich their Familes by Induſtry, Labour, and finally by many perils; ſo (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture) women are naturally weak that they may more diligently manage their Houſhold concerns: for fear cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out care, nor care without vigilance. What availeth it to bring much home, unleſs the wife will keep, preſerve, and diſtribute it? for what elſe is fabulouſly written concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Daughters of <hi>Danaus,</hi> who, filling a bored Hogſhead, were tormented with a perpetual and vain labour? My opinion is (which I hope, O <hi>Laurentius,</hi> that you will approve) that no ſmall advantages ariſe from this the Wives cuſtody: For truly that was well ſaid by <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> that moſt prudent perſon, <hi>Alexander</hi> would have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="014" facs="tcp:108455:57"/> far more renown and profit, if he could have kept and defended what he had gotten, than by the aſſiſtance of Fortune to have atchieved the greateſt matters: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wives ought not to be defrauded of their praiſe, if they ſhall order whatſoever is placed at home, as it is their duty; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſhould endeavour to remember that as dayly <hi>Pericles</hi> at <hi>Athens,</hi> ſo they ſhould govern their Families, and ſhould be willing always to judge themſelves, leſt they be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in their care, performance, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence about Domeſtick Affairs: It greatly conduceth to this matter, if they (which chiefly belongeth to them) accuſtom them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſtay at home, and to take care of all things: where I remember that prudent Groom, who, when he was asked what chiefly made an Horſe fat, ſaid, the Maſters Eye. Which duty that it might be recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to poſterity, an ordinary Shoe, and a Diſtaff and Spindle were affixed to the Brazen Statue of <hi>Caja Cecilia</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Tarquinnius,</hi> that thoſe things might in a manner ſignifie, that her diligent reſidence at home ſhould be imitated by Poſterity. What negligent Farmer can hope to have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious Husbandmen? What ſlothful Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral can make his Souldiers vigilant for the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:108455:57"/> Common-wealth? If therefore the Wife would have her Maids ſtay at home, ſhe ſhould not only inſtruct them by words, but ſhe ſhould demonſtrate, ſhew, and declare by her actions, what they ought to perform. Nothing truly is more excellent in Family Affairs, than that every thing be placed in its own ſtation, for order, than nothing which is more decent, nothing more uſeful, is always of the greateſt importance: We may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a company of Singers and Armies, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom unleſs a proportion be aptly obſerved, they can be termed nothing leſs than either Armies or Singers. I would have Wives to imitate the Ringleaders of Bees, who know, receive, and preſerve whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is placed within their Hives, and, until the neceſſity of their concerns ſhall other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe require, they are always preſent with their Honey-combs, that they may be exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitely and maturely perfected: Wives may ſend abroad their Men and Maid-ſervants, if they perceive it will be advantageous to them; but if they be uſeful at home, they may require, urge, and command their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. They ſhould judge it to appertain to their duty, that no dammage accrue to their Husbands in the Pantry, Wine-cellar, and Oyl-cellar: As Generals often view the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:108455:58"/> numbers of their Souldiers; ſo Wives ſhould often and moſt diligently recogniſe thoſe things which are placed at home, leſt at laſt, to their great detriment, they ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that what ſhould be of a years, ſcarce is of a months duration. The Cuſtom of <hi>Pericles</hi> greatly deceives unskilful perſons, and oftentimes impedes the Family Affairs, who ſold together all the fruits which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from his fields, and afterwards he provided, from the Market, whatſoever he had need of at home from day to day: for this daily manner of providing Corn, and Wine, and Wood, is rather fit for a Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and an unſetled Souldier, than a Citizen, and a Maſter of a Family; neither do they ſo liberally, ſo ſplendidly, nor ſo profitably provide for their Riches. But if any one ſhall object, That he hath obſerved this to be the fault of the Caterer, (even in my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) he ſhould judge, that the negligence of the Agents of the Wife is rather to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, than the Opinion of the wiſeſt men: I think this ſhould be imitated from the <hi>Roman</hi> Cuſtom, That the moſt noble Women ſhould not be employed in the vileſt things; for the noble Women, by the League that was made with the <hi>Sabines,</hi> were enfranchiſed from the Employments of the Mill, and Kitchen, and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:108455:58"/> ſervile Services: But indeed if the ſickneſs of the Husband, or an occaſion of honouring of Gueſts ſhall happen, they may undertake ſuch kind of Employment; for if it may conduce to the health of the Husband, not onely nothing ſhould be pretermitted, but we deteſt any omiſſion. I am infinitely plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſee, in that moſt Learned Poet and Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher <hi>Homer,</hi> that <hi>Andromache</hi> had ſo great love and affection for her <hi>Hector,</hi> that ſhe was diligent and exact, even in giving Hay to his Horſes, in which the Honour and Life of her Husband conſiſted. Therefore if a Wife ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies her mind to her Duty and her Honour, ſhe will acknowledge, that all things are due to, and ſhe will perform all things for her Husband: but if a liberal Husband ſhall purpoſe nobly to entertain ſome Perſons at his Houſe, ſhe ſhould not refuſe even the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Kitchen: which was not unknown to thoſe generous and moſt valiant Perſons <hi>Achilles</hi> and <hi>Patroclus,</hi> to whom when <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> and <hi>Ajax</hi> came to be reconciled, having laid by his Harp, he managed thoſe things with great diligence, which unleſs they had been decent for the ſake of Friendſhip or Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, ſcarce ſeemed fit for mean Servants. But enough of theſe things, foraſmuch as we propoſed briefly to recite, but not to inſtruct
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:108455:59"/> in each particular; eſpecially becauſe this Point is more diligently and more copiouſly diſcuſſed in the Diſcourſes of Learned Men, than I can now treat of it. Wherefore we ſhall proceed to the remaining Matters.</p>
                  <p>It is meet now (as we have promiſed) to ſpeak concerning Servants, who, if they be not neglected, will be very ornamental, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and delightful. This will be ſo effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, if they ſhall inſtruct them exactly, nor be angry with them before they diſcover that they have offended after admonition. I would have Wives imitate the Ring-leaders of the Bees (as in a manner in other things, ſo alſo in this part) who ſuffer none to be ſlothful, none negligent among them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>M. Cato</hi> the elder ſo diligently obſerved this Precept of domeſtick care, that if he perceived that his Servants were deficient in the duty of good Men, he preſently ſold thoſe Servants although old, and judged it by no means expedient to keep unprofitable Servants at his Houſe. Wives ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it to be an honourable employment for them to make ignorant Maid ſervants skilful, and to her, whom by experience in leſſer matters they obſerve to be endued with faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and diligence, they may diſpoſe the cuſtody of the Cellar. And thrifty Perſons
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:108455:59"/> ſhould conſtantly ſearch for and approve ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Caterers, and receive them with courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous words, and be bountiful to them, that by theſe great kindneſſes they might daily more earneſtly excite their diligence. They ſhould allow ſuch Food to their Servants as may be ſufficient for their nature, and their conſtant labour. They ſhould ſo handſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Cloth their Servants that they might ſeem to have a regard to Nature, Place, and Time. Furthermore according to the Opinion of <hi>Heſiod,</hi> they ſhould always beware of thoſe Servants who cannot be ſeparated from Children and Relations; for of neceſſity they will nouriſh themſelves together with theirs, even by ſtealth. Alſo they ſhould think it a decent thing, if any one of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily be ſick that the Perſon be taken care of with certain extraordinary diligence; for this is a courteſie and civility by which they will make them all diligent in and deſirous of the welfare of the Family: which (that we may return to the ſame Example) we plainly perceive in Bees, who never forſake their Ring-leader, becauſe of his great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence for, and care over them, and always follow him, whereſoever he goes, with great indications of their good will to him. This ſhould not ſeem ſtrange to any, becauſe alſo
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:108455:60"/> other Creatures are not deficient in an imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of gratitude; which evidently appears, as well by very many others, as by the next Example. The <hi>Athenians</hi> in the <hi>Perſian</hi> War, that they might provide for their ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, forſaking their Walls committed the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens to the Sea: they haſtily departing from the Shore, the Dog of <hi>Xantippus</hi> the elder, was grieved at his abſence (which he mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly ſhewed, by his running, wagging his Tail, howling, and barking) unleſs he went along with his Maſter: therefore whilſt he ſwimmed in the midſt of the waves to his Maſters Ship, <hi>Xantippus</hi> who was flying ſtood ſtill and received the ſorrowful Dog. Afterwards leſt this matter, which was wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of remembrance, ſhould be forgotten, when his Dog died he erected an honourable Sepulchre for him, in a certain noble place (which for a long time after was called <hi>Dogs-Grave)</hi> that he might leave a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Monument to Poſterity, of a mutual kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to be preſerved between Maſters and Servants. In this manner it will be moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, that as in Military Affairs, Legates, Tribunes, Centurions, and in the City Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Treaſurers, and ſuch kind of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates have the government of peculiar mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: that managing few things they may
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:108455:60"/> exactly per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orm their Offices; ſo if Wives would take care of their Family-buſineſs, they ſhould ſo ſeparate the Office of inſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the employments of drudgery, that it may be manifeſt what ſhould be done by every one, and what may be expected from them. Unleſs each Perſons place be aſſign'd him in a Ship, all things will be tumultuous, although no Tempeſt aſſail them. We know that Heaven it ſelf (which is an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Manſion for us) is compoſed with ſo great a concatenation of things, that one part is linked to another; and all are aptly fixed together: By the ſtrings of Harps, if they be well tuned, one Harmony is made of divers Notes, than which nothing is more pleaſant, nothing more melodious to the Ears; ſo if Wives ſhall appoint Stations to theis Concerns, and Offices to their Servants, they will perceive that thoſe things will greatly conduce to their ſplendour and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit; therefore (as I have ſaid before) they ſhould receive, preſerve, and diſtribute with care, prudence, and decency, thoſe things which are brought home: and they ſhould moſt exactly perform, whatſoever things may be ſet in order and meliorated, by care and diligence, that the dignity of their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may be confirmed and increaſed. But theſe things ſhall ſuffice.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:108455:61"/>
                  <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Concerning the Education of Children.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE education of Children, the moſt commodious, and by far the moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant part of the Wifes duty, remains. Diligence in Family Affairs in the accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Riches availeth, in a manner, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing (as that ancient <hi>Crates</hi> was wont to ſay) unleſs a great care, and a certain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary induſtry be beſtowed in the edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and inſtruction of the Children, to whom they are left; by this matter alſo they are greatly obliged to their Parents (to whom they owe all things) by whom they muſt neceſſarily and truly ſeem deſerted and forſaken, unleſs their Parents ſhall perform the duty of maintaining and inſtructing them: for truly we muſt acknowledge that all things are due to the Authors of our Life, which naturally all Mortals deſire, and with great reaſon preſerve. What great things ſhould we atchieve, if a generous education ſhall accompany our noble birth? wherein (if
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:108455:61"/> you ſhall diligently conſider all things in your mind and thoughts) you may obſerve that (if Mothers do not derogate from Nature it ſelf) the duty of education ſo appertaineth to them, that they cannot refuſe it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the violation of many duties; for it in every reſpect denotes a propenſe love to their Children, whom Nature doth not at all neglect: which that it may be more evidently demonſtrated, I ſhould now diſcourſe concerning the Procreation of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren before their birth: but time will not permit me to digreſs more largely, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelf hath ſo ſecluded and ſo obſconded thoſe parts, that thoſe things which cannot be beheld without ſhame, can ſcarce be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of by us with honour. But we will declare thoſe things which cannot be omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Nature it ſelf carefully exhibits ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Iſſue, till it attaineth its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time of birth; moreover, Nature affords the nouriſhment of Milk to all living Creatures which bring forth, and hath given them Breaſts, like overflowing Fountains, by which the young one being nouriſhed, may by degrees be augmented and corrobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated in the Parts of its Body; ſhe hath alſo therefore given them two Paps, that if they brought forth Twins they might eaſily ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:108455:62"/> and nouriſh them together; which things although they are tranſacted with great wiſdom, yet they would ſeem done in vain, if ſhe had not Implanted in them a certain ſtupendious love and affection to their Iſſue. Where the peculiar care and diligence of Nature may be obſerved, for whereas ſhe hath placed other Creatures Paps under their Bellies, ſhe hath ſo affixed Womens Breaſts to their Boſoms, that they might both ſuckle them with their Milk and cheriſh them with their embraces, and eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and conveniently kiſs them, and (as it is ſaid) receive them into their Boſoms; for ſo ſhe hath aſſigned to them the capacity of bringing forth, and the duty of education, not only of neceſſity, but of her ſingular love and good will: that which we perceive in the terrible Bear and ſavage Beaſts is alſo a great argument (if they would imitate them) to induce Women to employ their greateſt care in adorning their Children<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; who after ſhe hath brought forth her miſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Cub, formeth and poliſheth it with her Tongue, as it were with ſome Inſtrument, ſo that ſhe may moſt rightly be termed not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Dam of the Cub, but alſo the Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer. Why ſhould we inſiſt upon theſe ſmall matters? Nature concedeth ſo great a love
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:108455:62"/> to Iſſue, that we may perceive Brutes which of themſelves are fearful, hereby become moſt bold, and thoſe which were negligent, moſt ſubtle, and thoſe which were greedy, moſt ſparing. Did not alſo the Bird, in <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> ſuffer hunger that it might provide food for its young ones, and to ſupply them, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauded its own Belly? Therefore Mothers will deſerve grievous reproaches, if they neglect the care of their Children, and live careleſly. I would have them to refuſe no pains to obtain moſt excellent aſſociates, aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and comforters in their old age: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if Mothers would be innocent they ſhould not neglect their Children, but (that they may provide for their Souls and Bodies) they ſhould cheriſh them and ſuckle them, whom, being unknown, they nouriſhed with their own Blood, being now born, now Men and Women, now known, now dear, and they ſhould themſelves, as well as they could, educate them; it is not only the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a Nurſe, but alſo of a careful Mother. The Wife of <hi>Marcus Cato</hi> the Cenſor ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led her Infant with her own Milk, which Cuſtome continueth among the <hi>Roman</hi> Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men even to this Age. Moreover becauſe a Society in Meat and Drink increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth love and friendſhip, that ſhe might ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:108455:63"/> the Children of her Servants well affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to her Infant, ſhe ſometimes gave them ſuck: whom we deſire and exhort the beſt W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>men to imitate, eſpecially ſince it is highly important, that in whoſe Womb, and of whoſe Blood the In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ant was conceived, it ſhould alſo by her be nouriſhed; for no nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment ſeems more fit, none more whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, than that the ſame aliment, which is endued with much heat and vigour, and which is a known a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d familiar Food, ſhould be given to the Children; whoſe efficacie is ſuch, that in the forming the properties of the Body and Mind it is almoſt equivalent to the Virtue of the ſpermatick faculty: this is evidently perceived in many things, Kids be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuckled with Sheeps Milk, their Hair will by degrees become more ſoft; but if Lambs be ſuckled by Goats, it is certain that their Fleeces will become more rough: In Trees it is certain that there is a greater efficacy both in the Sap and Soil, than in Children; for although they be pleaſant and chearful, yet if they be removed to anothers Lap, you may obſerve them much endamaged, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly changed by the Milk of the Nurſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore noble Women ſhould endeavour to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> their Children, left the aliment of a worſe and engrafted Milk ſhould cauſe them to
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:108455:63"/> degenerate; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut if (as it often happens) the Mothers cannot, for juſt cauſes, ſuckle their Children, they ſhould think that they ſhould take, and ſubſtitute in their Office, Nurſes, not Slaves, nor ſtrangers, nor drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, nor unchaſte Women, but them who are free born, well humoured and endued with curious Language, leſt the young In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant ſhould imbibe corrupt manners and words, and, with the very Milk ſucking turpitude, errours, and impure infirmities, it ſhould, by a degenerate body and mind, be infected with pernicious contagions: for as the Joints of an Infant may be rightly formed and joined together, ſo from their Childhood their Manners may be exactly and aptly compoſed; therefore they ſhould be curious in the choice of Nurſes; this age and this as yet pliant mind is moſt eaſie to faſhion; for as we Imprint a Seal upon ſoft Wax, ſo the diſpoſitions and diſtempers of the Nurſe are wont to be Engraven upon Children; whoſe inclination and nature how prevalent it is, that moſt prudent Poet <hi>Maro</hi> demonſtrates, who relateth, that <hi>Dido</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Aeneas</hi> not only fierce, but cruel, ſaid, The <hi>Hircanian</hi> Tygers gave you ſuck: alſo that moſt pleaſant Poet <hi>Theocritus</hi> complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of the ſame, deteſting the cruel <hi>Cupid,</hi>
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:108455:64"/> not becauſe he was born of his Mother <hi>Venus,</hi> but becauſe he had ſucked the Paps of a Lioneſs. Wherefore they ſhould think it beſt, and very decent, and commendable to ſuckle their Children, whom they ſhould nouriſh with great love, faithfulneſs and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, or to commit this part of their duty to well inſtructed Nurſes, who may eſteem and love them, not with a feigned and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary diligence.</p>
                  <p>After they have paſſed their infancy, the mothers ſhould imploy their Wit, Care, and endeavour to qualifie them with excellent endowments of mind and body; firſt they ſhould teach them their duty to the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal God, to their Country and Parents, that they may accuſtom them from their infancie to reliſh that, which is the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of other virtues; they will approve themſelves to be the moſt hopeful, who fear God, obey the Laws, honour their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, reverence their Superiours, are affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to their Equals, and courteous to their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours; therefore they ſhould entertain all men with a civil aſpect, countenance, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally obliging words; but they ſhould moſt familiarly converſe with the beſt Perſons; they ſhould ſo learn Temperance in Meat and Drink, that they may lay, as it were, the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:108455:64"/> foundation of Abſtinence for their future Lives: Mothers ſhould admoniſh them to avoid thoſe Pleaſures which are diſhonoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: Children ſhould apply their endeavour, mind, and thoughts to theſe things, which may be ornamental, uſeful, and delightful in greater matters: If Mothers inſtruct their Children in theſe things, they will much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more eaſily obtain the aſſiſtances of Learning. Oftentimes we ſee the Commands and Gifts of Princes moſt welcom to their Subjects, although yet the ſame, proceeding from private Perſons, ſcarce ſeem acceptable. Who is ignorant how much authority the mild and jejune ſpeech of a Parent beareth with Children? Wherefore that wiſe <hi>Cato</hi> the Elder, that he might not be deficient in the duty of a Father to his Children, he dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently taught them as well many other things, as Literature: Alſo the barbarous <hi>Eurydice</hi> ſeems worthy of great praiſe; ſhe being now ancient, applied her ſelf to Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that Monument of Virtue and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, that ſhe might not only be the Author of Life to her Children, but that, by her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, ſhe might leave to them many condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Liberal Sciences. Mothers ſhould often premoniſh their Children to reſtrain themſelves from exceſſive Laughter, and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merarious
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:108455:65"/> Speeches; for that denotes Folly, this Fury. Moreover they ſhould take heed, that they do not ordinarily diſcourſe of thoſe things which are odious to act: therefore they ſhould reſtrain them from filthy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachful Speeches; and if they ſhall ſpeak any thing too licentiouſly and obſcenely, they ſhould not receive it with mirth or a kiſs, but with a whip. Furthermore, they ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them, not to upbraid any perſons with their Poverty, or ignominy of their Anceſtors, or other Calamities, whereby they will both procure to themſelves grievous enmities, and imbibe a cuſtom of arrogating: They ſhould teach them Sports, in which they may ſo vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily undertake Labours, that, if occaſion ſhall require, they may more eaſily ſuſtain thoſe which are more grievous. I would have Mothers to avoid in the preſence of their Children, anger, avarice, and concupiſcence, whereby vertue languiſheth, that from their infancy they may contemn, ſhun, and hate theſe moſt filthy ſeducers, and that they may be greatly careful to reverence ſacred Names, and be afraid to revile them, for whom being grown up will they not deride, who at that age contemn the Divine Nature? It is of ſo great importance to accuſtom them in their Childhood, that they muſt eſpecially admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:108455:65"/> them to abſtain from ſwearing: Neither truly do they deſerve belief who commonly ſwear, even for the ſake of the moſt vile matter; and they who ordinarily ſwear, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes unwarily forſwear themſelves: Mothers ſhould accuſtome their Children to ſpeak the truth; this was moſt noble among the <hi>Perſians,</hi> and therefore they ordained, that there ſhould be no Markets of Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe among them, for they believed it to be a place of lying and forſwearing: Mothers ſhould teach them to ſpeak little, unleſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, as well in other places as at Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets, leſt (which ſhould be moſt eſtranged from that Age) they ſhould become impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and talkative; for it will be a hindrance to their knowledge, if they pretend wiſely to declare, what they do not ſufficiently comprehend: therefore that was a witty ſaying of <hi>Cato,</hi> who, being then a young Man, when he was blamed for his ſilence, ſaid, It will not be at all troubleſome to me, untill I know thoſe things which are unfit to be concealed: If they ſhall learn many things of this kind from their Mothers, as ſoon as their age will permit, they may more happily and more eaſily acquire the gravity and diſcipline of their Parents. There are many other things, which becauſe they are
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:108455:66"/> rather proper to Fathers, I for the preſent omit, and therefore the rather, becauſe I ſeem to ſee ſome who will term this our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of Wedlock immenſe and infinite, which the Fathers of our Age can ſcarce ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently treat of; there is nothing which I can more truly anſwer to theſe Perſons than this, truly I never intended to diſcuſs, what might be done, but to declare, what ought to be done. Who is ſo unjuſt a Judge, that if upon juſt cauſes (even as you) he ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove Marriages, and ſhall, in the choice of a Wife, receive a Woman excellent in Manners, Age, Extraction, Beauty, and Riches, who is loving to her Husband, who is modeſt, and who is very skilfull in the management of domeſtick affairs; who, I ſay, is ſo miſtaken in affairs, that he can hope for all theſe great things, and can imagine that ſuch Wives ought not to perform all greater matters? Therefore (O my <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentius)</hi> your equals ſhould follow your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample with great diligence (who have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to Wife <hi>Zinebia,</hi> a Virgin flouriſhing with Virtue, Beauty, a Noble Family, and abundant Riches) and in the imitation of you they ought to be animated. For what more illuſtrious, what more worthy Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple can I propoſe than yours? ſince you,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:108455:66"/> who are moſt worthy of your Father, Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, and your moſt renowned Anceſtors, have choſen ſuch a Wife, in that moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous City of <hi>Italy, Florence,</hi> whoſe Riches indeed all Perſons, but whoſe continence, faithfulneſs, and prudence, all good Men ſo highly eſteem and admire, that they think her bleſſed and happy in you alone, and you fortunate and truly happy in ſuch a Wife: who becauſe ye have obtained the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and adorned conjugal qualifications, they beſeech the immortal God, that ye may have the beſt Children, and the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Citizens of the Commonwealth.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things perchance might ſeem incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, becauſe they are treated of by me, if they were not in a manner recognized in your Nuptials: ſo truly young perſons, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing your example, will profit more, than if they only acquieſce in my writings, for even as Laws are greatly advantageous to a City, when it is known that an excellent Prince obeys them; ſo ſince your Example alſo is conſentaneous to our Precepts, we hope that it will be imitated by young per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. But (O <hi>Laurentius)</hi> as my diſcourſe began, ſo it ſhall be terminated, in you. You have now my opinion concerning Wedlock, inſtead of a Preſent; in which I hope what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:108455:67"/> is ſaid by me (not to admoniſh you, as I ſaid at the firſt, but to declare my affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to you) will be kindly accepted by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but I certainly know that it will be favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably you in whoſe name I undertook this Tract. If any thing perchance in theſe our little Commentaries ſhall occur to you, in the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which is wiſely and learnedly written, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute it to that excellent perſon in all kind of praiſe, <hi>Zacharias Triviſanus,</hi> (for I willingly commemorate him) and to the <hi>Grecian</hi> Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, out of which I have collected ſome things which pertains to this matter, and have purpoſely inſerted them here. Having been ſcarce converſant a few Months in theſe things I ſeem to have gathered great and pleaſant advantages. Very great is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geny and diligence of that excellent and moſt learned <hi>Guarinus</hi> of <hi>Verona</hi> (who being my Schoolmaſter and loving Friend I am familiar with) who was my conduct, together with many of our moſt worthy perſons, both in the undertaking and beginning the ſtudy of the Liberal Sciences; and he was ſuch a Guide, that by his aſſiſtance theſe noble ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies (to which I have applyed my ſelf from my infancy) are become much more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and pleaſant to me. Therefore you will willingly accept this (as I may ſo call it,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:108455:67"/> the Wives Necklace) from me in theſe your Marriages, which I know that you will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther therefore greatly eſteem, becauſe it is of that ſort that it cannot (as other Neck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces may) be broken and worn out by uſe, or becauſe it proceeds from the greateſt ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and a moſt faithful mind entirely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to you.</p>
                  <trailer>Farewel.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>
               <hi>Poggius</hi> ſaluteth <hi>Guarinus</hi> of <hi>Verona.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MAY the Gods beſhrow thoſe moſt wicked Letter-Carriers, who treat us ſo ill in delivering our Epiſtles, and deprive me of the fruit of my Letters, you of the pleaſure, which according to your very great good will to me, you are wont to receive from them. But I give you many thanks for the little Book which you ſent to me: I had been infinitely indebted to you, if I had been about to marry a Wife; but before I cared but little for taking a Wife, now not at all, foraſmuch as I ſee ſo many and ſo great things are, in the judgment of wiſe men, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the duty of a Wife, which we may rather wiſh for than hope to obtain. But theſe things in jeaſt. When firſt the Book
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:108455:68"/> was delivered to me, I read it ſo haſtily, (being pleaſed as well with the Novelty of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, as the order and pleaſantneſs of the Diſcourſe) that I read over the whole Book in one day, but afterwards I reviewed it more deliberately; indeed the matter is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and ſweet, and adorned with very many Examples, but ſo diſpoſed into order, that nothing could be diſcuſſed more methodical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but that which pleaſeth me moſt, is the gravity of ſpeech which it conſtantly retains. <hi>Franciſcus Barbarus</hi> ſeems to me to have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten another Book of Offices (but belonging to Wives) he ſo exactly imitates <hi>Cicero</hi> in his diſcourſe: You know I am not a Flatterer, thoſe things I ſpeak come from the thoughts of my mind. There is a certain dignity in his Sentences, joined with the greateſt elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, worthy of any the moſt grave per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. I would have you to exhort our <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcus</hi> to write, for he publickly produceth admirable Firſt-fruits. Our <hi>Gentius</hi> hath read and approveth the Book; moreover <hi>Blaſius</hi> of the <hi>Guaſcons;</hi> I will publiſh it, where I ſhall perceive any advantage of Glory and Renown can be obtained. Furthermore (O my <hi>Guarinus)</hi> I have received from you a much worthy, though ſmall, Epiſtle, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you moſt eloquently deſcribe the Naval
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:108455:68"/> Victory which the <hi>Venetians</hi> obtained, with exceeding Valour, over the moſt wicked E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of our whole Race: And when I ſhewed to many perſons that that Epiſtle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely pleaſed me, to them it ſeemed that thoſe things were evidently and nobly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by you. But of theſe things elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
               <dateline>From <hi>Conſtance, </hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Decemb.</hi> 31.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>Paulus Vergerius <hi>ſaluteth the moſt Learned Perſon,</hi> Nicholaus Leontinus <hi>the Philoſopher.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis day I found a little Book, with my Lord <hi>Franciſcus,</hi> Cardinal of <hi>Florence,</hi> when I came to wait upon him, who ſtays at home to recover his health, which <hi>Franciſcus Barbarus,</hi> your friend and fellow Student, hath lately publiſhed concerning Wedlock, indeed elegant; and even as it is excellent in the beauty of language, ſo alſo it abounds with the beſt Precepts and moſt copious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples collected out of Greek and Latine Hiſtory. I admire in this Tract not ſo much the wit as the diligence of this perſon; for I eaſily perceived that indeed long ſince; that
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:108455:69"/> deareſt perſon <hi>Zacharius Triviſanus</hi> long ſince ſhewing me a certain Epiſtle of his, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though written, as it were, negligently and without any ſtudy; but that now a young man and one unexperienced in Nuptial Affairs ſhould write ſo learnedly and ſo elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently concerning Wedlock, and ſhould be ſo knowing in that, which he is, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally ignorant of, this is that which I cannot highly enough admire. Therefore now no body will deny that he is truly a Grecian but an exellent Latiniſt, he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and underſtandeth ſo well: But he can by no means ſeem barbarous, who thinketh or writeth nothing barbarous; and I wiſh all other barbarouſneſs may be ſo barbarous. But I greatly blame you becauſe you gave me no notice of that little Book, ſince you, who were his fellow Student, could not be ignorant of it. I ſuppoſe that you did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that the rumour of Fame would bring it to me, and when it had been common in the hands of all others, then at laſt it ſhould come to me, which truly I do not approve; and unleſs you ſhall alledge a better reaſon, I cannot but condemn.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> Conſtance, <date>
                     <hi>April</hi> 10.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:108455:69"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
